(
"ai_sub_version": "3.6.0",
"generated_at": "2026-10-10T23:14:28.428417",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.7-flash",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"service_tier": null,
"service_tier_subtitles": null,
"service_tier_lyrics": null,
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
グッドモーニングのじゃ〜
Good morning, noja~
のじゃ〜〜
Noja~~
よいしょ
All right...
ふあああ〜
Ahhh...
挨拶するのじゃ
Time to do my greeting, noja.
あらあら メラメラ 火知メラー！
Ara-ara, mera-mera! Achichi Mela!
ホロライブ アソビまわり隊
From hololive's Asobi Mawaridai...
ご利益担当の火消し屋サラマンダー、火知メラなのじゃ〜！
...the blessing-dispensing firefighter salamander, Achichi Mela, noja~!
のじゃ？
Noja?
BGM２つになった？
Did the BGM start playing twice?
のじゃ
Noja.
どうじゃ？
How is it?
おはようのじゃ〜！
Good morning, noja~!
グッドモーニング or
Good morning, or...
グッドイブニング or
...good evening, or...
ハローなの...
...hello, no...
のじゃ
Noja.
え？
Eh?
の...
No...
のじゃ〜！
Noja~!
のじゃ〜
Noja~
だい、大丈夫〜？
Is—is everything okay?
き、聞こえる〜？
C-Can you hear me?
聞こえるのじゃ〜？
Can you hear me, noja~?
のじゃ〜
Noja~
You guys OK?
オッケーのじゃ？
Are you okay, noja?
オンライン〜？
Online~?
I'm back?
あっ
Ah.
センキューのじゃ〜〜
Thank you, noja~~
うん
Yeah.
オッケー
Okay.
よかった〜〜
Thank goodness~~
センキューのじゃ〜〜
Thank you, noja~~
のじゃ
Noja.
切れちゃったっぽい
Looks like it cut out.
えっと...
Um...
ちょっと待ってほしいのじゃ
I need you to wait a moment, noja.
Please wait a moment, noja.
なんか設定が難しくて...
The settings are kind of difficult, and...
あんまりまだ分かってない
I don't really understand them yet.
よいしょ
All right...
え、また切れた？
Eh, did it cut out again?
What? What?
のじゃ？
Noja?
ん？
Hm?
今、オッケー？
Is it okay now?
Okay now?
ラグい？
Is it laggy?
BGM再び？
Is the BGM double again?
のじゃ〜〜！
Noja~~!
トラブル、many, many トラブル！
Trouble, many, many trouble!
ソーリー
Sorry...
ソーリーなのじゃ
Sorry, noja.
ど、どうしよう
Wh-What should I do?
ソーリーのじゃ
Sorry, noja.
のじゃ〜〜
Noja~~
オッケー？
Okay?
オッケー！
Okay!
のじゃ〜！ 朝からごめんのじゃ〜〜！
Noja~! Sorry for this so early in the morning, noja~~!
よいしょ、よいしょ、よいしょ、よいしょ
Yoisho, yoisho, yoisho, yoisho...
もう...
Geez...
朝なのに モーニングなのに
Even though it's morning—even though it's morning...
いっぱいトラブル...
...so much trouble...
いっぱいトラブルで、あの、起きた
With all this trouble, um, I woke up.
I wake up
うん、逆にね
Yeah, ironically.
逆に起きたのじゃ
It actually woke me right up, noja.
おはよう なのじゃ〜〜！
Good morning, noja~~!
うわ〜、あのね
Whoa~ You know what?
あのね、あのね
Listen, listen.
今日は「のじゃEnglish」だから
Because today is "Noja English"...
いっぱい寝た
...I slept a lot.
あの...
Um...
8時間寝た
I slept for 8 hours.
I sleep...
8 hour？
"8 hour"?
合ってる？
Is that right?
うん
Yeah.
早く寝たよ、昨日10時？
I went to bed early. Yesterday at 10:00?
22時に寝た。
I went to bed at 22:00.
22時に寝ましたのじゃ。
I went to bed at 22:00, noja.
今日の朝のために。
For the sake of this morning.
それでね、6時...
And then, 6:00...
6に起きた。
I woke up at 6:00.
うん
Yeah.
いっぱい寝ましたのじゃ。
I slept a lot, noja.
そっちはまだ夜？
Is it still nighttime over there?
You guys...
night? night?
Japan is morning.
午後6時？
6:00 PM?
6... PM...
5 AM...
or evening?
そうだ、eveningだ。
Right, it's evening.
11 PM.
いっぱいの時間！
So many different times!
many timeや、many time。
Many times, many times!
That's nice. 深夜...
That's nice. Late night...
うーん...
Hmm...
そうそう、つづり？つづりと今日子？
Oh yeah, Tsuduri? Tsuduri and Kyoko?
あの、遊び回り隊メンバーの、つづり＆今日子は、
The members of Asobimawaritai, Tsuduri and Kyoko,
あの、ストリー...ストリーミングなの？
are, like, strea... streaming?
ずっとね、あの、配信？
Have they been streaming this whole time?
バロラント？バロラント？オーバーウォッチ？
Valorant? Valorant? Overwatch?
ごめん、げ...ゲームが、ちゃんと理解できてない。
Sorry, I don't really understand ga... games well.
あのー、FPS... FPSの、
Um, an FPS... an FPS...
なんか耐久配信をしてた。
some kind of endurance stream they were doing.
そう、ロング、ロングストリームをね、してた。
Yeah, they were doing a long, long stream.
オーバーウォッチ！
Overwatch!
オーバーウォッチをね、してた。
They were streaming Overwatch.
うん。
Yeah.
「今から2枠目」めっちゃ頑張ってるのじゃ、すごいのじゃー！
"Starting round 2 now"—they're trying so hard!
ねえ！
Right?!
耐久なのじゃー。
An endurance stream, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
Crazy! 確かに！確かにめっちゃ長い！
Crazy! Seriously! That really is super long!
うん、体力、体力すごいのじゃ！
Yeah, their stamina is incredible, noja!
うん。
Yeah.
なんか気合い入れてたよ。うん。
They were really pumped up. Yeah.
で、メラは、English...
And Mela was going to do an English...
study streamをするんじゃが、
study stream, but...
あのね、あの、
you know, um...
前回のDuolingoの配信で、
during the last Duolingo stream,
あの、主らめっちゃ簡単って思わなかった？
didn't you guys think it was way too easy?
あのー、
Uhm...
I thought Duolingo was too easy,
あの、前のstream。
um, in the previous stream.
そうで思って、
So I thought that,
そう、I tried、あの、test skipping。
and so, I tried, um, test skipping.
そう、飛び級？飛び級しようと思って。
Yeah, skipping ahead? I decided to skip ahead.
I tried skipping ahead to Section 3?
そう、Section 2をやってて、too easyだったから、
Yeah, I was doing Section 2 and it was too easy, so...
あのー、スキップしようとしたの。
um, I tried to skip it.
そう。
Yeah.
But! しかし、あの、I failed!
But! However, um, I failed!
そう！
Yeah!
あの、難しくて、
Um, it was so hard...
It's hard for me. そう、難しかった。
It's hard for me. Yeah, it was difficult.
難しくて、あのー、
It was so hard, and, um...
Section 3が、
Section 3 was...
あの、駄目、駄目だった！I can't skip!
um, no good, it was no good! I can't skip!
そう。
Yeah.
Too difficult for me.
そう、駄目じゃった。
Yeah, it was totally no good.
から、あのー、またいつか挑戦する。
So, um, I will try again someday.
うん、またいつか挑戦する。
Yeah, I'll challenge it again someday.
から、Basicからやろうと思うのじゃ。
So I think I'll start from the basics, noja.
え、もう一回主らと一緒にやってみる？
Wait, want to try doing it together with you guys again?
今日の朝やって駄目だったやつ、もう一回主らとやってみる？
Try the one I failed this morning together with you guys?
ちょ、どんなのか見てみる？一旦。
Wait, want to take a look at what it's like? For a bit.
一旦見てみろ、主ら。
Take a look once, you guys.
You... you guys... want see... test?
見たい？
Want to see?
じゃ、一回見せてあげる。
Then I'll show you once.
一回見せてあげるのじゃ。うん。
I'll show you once, noja. Yeah.
えっと、じゃあ、お勉強のお部屋に行こうと思うから...
Uhm, so I think we'll head over to the study room, so...
あ！
Ah!
You... guys... already push like...
already like my video?
グッドボタンを押してくれましたかのじゃ？
Did you already hit the thumbs up button, noja?
Please subscribe to my channel,
and push like, グッドボタン to take off my...
and push like, thumbs up button to take off my...
maskのじゃー！
mask, noja!
あー
Ah...
Thank you のじゃー
Thank you, noja~!
じゃ、行くのじゃ
Well then, let's get going, noja.
よいしょ
All right.
うん
Mm.
よいしょ
Here we go.
おはよう、のじゃー
Good morning, noja~.
うん
Mm.
よいしょー
All right.
んで、えっと、I...
And, um, I...
えー、どれだっけ？
Uh, which one was it?
そう、This is section 2?
Right, "This is Section 2"?
前回やったのがこれね
This is the one we did last time.
前回やったのがこれで
What we did last time was this,
これがセクション2で
and this is Section 2...
This is section 2, and I tried this...
Section 3, I know some words in English.
そう。ちょっとは単語知ってますよ、英語の
Right. "I know some words in English."
そう、ちょっとは英単語知ってますの特に
Right, at the "I know some English words" part,
あの、飛び級しようと思って
I thought I'd skip ahead.
そう
Yeah.
I tried this...
そう、Actually I think I know some words in English.
Right. "Actually, I think I know some words in English."
知ってると思う
I think I do.
そう
Yeah.
自信ね！
It's all confidence!
わしは知ってるつもりじゃったから
Because I felt like I knew them,
これをやったんじゃけど
I took this test, but...
オッケー、I... 見せてあげる
Okay, I'll... I'll show you.
このテストをクリアして「セクション3」まで飛び級しよう！
"Clear this test to jump straight to Section 3!"
Pass this テスト to...
"Pass this test to..."
飛び級チャレンジ、セクション3
Skip challenge, Section 3.
うん
Mm.
で
And so,
やろうとしたの。充電する
what I tried to do: "充電する"...
チャージ
Charge.
Charge
あ、音聴こえるのしら？
Ah, can you hear the sound, I wonder?
Charge
でかいかな？
Is it too loud?
Is too big?
Charge
どう、じゃ？
How is it, noja?
Sounds good?
うるさい？
Too loud?
いい感じかの？
Is it about right?
大きい？オッケー、too big? オッケー。
Too loud? Okay, too big? Okay.
Charge
オッケー？It's okay?
Okay? It's okay?
Charge
いい感じか。オッケー、good. オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Sounds good? Okay, good. Okay, okay, okay.
じゃあ、これで。charge, 充電する。
Then let's go with this. "Charge", to charge.
待って、前回と問題違う！
Wait, the questions are different from last time!
問題が違うのじゃ！
The questions are different, noja!
オッケー
Okay.
次へ
Next.
Is this place safe?
Is this place safe? ここは...
"Is this place safe?" Here is...
ここは安全ですか？
"Is this place safe?"
安全ですか？えっ、今回簡単かも！前回よりも、
"Is it safe?" Wait, this might be easy this time! Even more than last time,
あの、easy, easyかも！
um, it might be easy, really easy!
前もっと簡単...難しかった
Before it was much easi—harder.
オッケー
Okay.
忘れる、forget
"忘れる", forget.
Forget
うん、うん。え、なんか前回より簡単かも！
Yeah, yeah. Huh, somehow this might be easier than last time!
え、運ゲーのじゃ？これ
Wait, is this an RNG game, noja?
Don't wear shoes inside.
Don't wear shoes inside. えっと、
"Don't wear shoes inside." Um,
室内で、
"indoors,"
えーっと...
um...
靴を履かないでください
"please do not wear shoes."
室内で靴を履かないでください
"Please do not wear shoes indoors."
オッケー
Okay.
え、運ゲー？ご利益担当なのじゃ？
Wait, RNG game? Is my divine blessing working, noja?
これ、もしかして、
Could this perhaps,
もしかしてこれ、あのー、配信...配信で運がいいわしのやつ、のじゃ？
perhaps be that streamer luck where I get lucky on stream, noja?
普段よりも実力が、あれか？
Is my skill showing more than usual, or something?
そう、question changed!
Yeah, the questions changed!
変わっちゃったのじゃ。バフが、バフが乗ってるのじゃ！
They totally changed, noja. I have a buff, a buff applied, noja!
橋、bridge
"橋", bridge.
Bridge
オッケー
Okay.
え、配信バフ可能性ありのじゃ
Wait, a stream buff is definitely possible, noja.
Bridge, 橋？
Bridge, bridge?
Don't drive on that road.
Don't drive on that road. えっと、その道で
"Don't drive on that road." Um, "on that road,"
運転しないで
"do not drive."
よいしょ
There we go.
え、easy!
Wait, easy!
待って、
Wait,
楽しむ、have fun
"楽しむ", have fun.
Have fun
え、
Wait,
Duolingo is watching my stream?
Is Duolingo watching my stream?
Duolingo見てる？Hurry! You're...
Is Duolingo watching? "Hurry! You're..."
...late
遅いから早よせい！
You're late, so hurry it up!
オッケー。え、待って、まだライフが3ある
Okay. Wait, I still have 3 hearts!
ライフ0になったのに
Even though my hearts hit 0 last time.
マジのじゃ？
Seriously, noja?
のじゃー
Noja~.
え、easy, easy
Wait, easy, easy.
オッケー、Be なんちゃら... This area is dangerous at night. Be careful のじゃ
Okay, "Be..." whatever... "This area is dangerous at night." "Be careful", noja.
Careful
え、easyのじゃ、easyのじゃ！
Wait, this is easy noja, so easy noja!
いくら使っていますか？
"How much are you spending?"
えー、How much...
Um, "How much..."
How much
...are you...
are you
...spending?
spending
じゃない？のじゃ！
Isn't it? Noja!
え！Easy, easy! Too easyのじゃ！Why? なんで？なんでのじゃ？
What! Easy, easy! Too easy noja! Why? Why? Why noja?
もっと難しかったのじゃ！
It was so much harder before, noja!
But I for...
But I for—
忘れたのじゃ。
I forgot.
I forgot!
どんな問題じゃったかも忘れたけど、なんかむず、むずっと思ったのじゃ。
I forgot what kind of question it was too, but I remember thinking it was hard.
I always spend too much...
なんちゃら at the store.
...something "...at the store."
money のじゃ。
It's "money"!
え？イージーすぎないのじゃ？
Huh? Isn't this too easy?
Why? なんで？
Why? Why?
のじゃー！
Nojaaa!
Too easy ですのじゃー！
This is too easy!
なんでー？
Why?
こんなのあり？こんなのあり？
Is this for real? Is it really this simple?
そのことは心配しないで。Don't worry about...
"Don't worry about that." Don't worry about...
Don't worry about that.
えー？待って、イージー、イージー！Why?
Huh? Wait, easy, easy! Why?
え、もしかしてわし、あのセクション4、よ、4、4チャレンジしてた？
Wait, could it be that I was attempting Section 4? F-Four?
のじゃ？
Noja?
Please come inside.
Please... come... inside.
おいしょ。
All right.
え？Too easy のじゃ。
Huh? Too easy.
Too easy のじゃ！
Too easy!
一緒に橋を渡ろう。
"Let's cross the bridge together."
えー...あ、これわかんない。
Uh... Oh, I don't know this one.
えー... Let's... Let's...
Um... Let's... Let's...
えー、渡るってなんじゃろ？
Um, what was "to cross"?
まぁいいや。Let's なんちゃら bridge... bridge...
Oh well. Let's something bridge... bridge...
together だと思うんだよ。together...
I think it's "together." Together...
Let's...渡るってなんじゃろ？
Let's... What is "to cross"?
Let's pass... pass とか。
Let's pass... maybe "pass"?
ちょ、一旦これで。のじゃ！
Wait, let's just go with this for now. Noja!
Cross the street!?
bridge じゃないのじゃ！？cross... cross...
It's not bridge?! Cross... cross...
あ、道！橋だと思った！
Ah, road! I thought it said bridge!
橋じゃない！
It wasn't bridge!
道なのじゃー！
It was road!
I thought bridge... 日本語、Japanese 間違えたのじゃ！
I thought bridge... My Japanese was wrong!
My Japanese is... bad のじゃ。
My Japanese is... bad.
Cross the street together のじゃ。
"Cross the street together", I see.
私たちはプールに泳ぎに行きます。
"We are going swimming at the pool."
We...
わしこういうの苦手！英訳超苦手！英訳超苦手！
I'm so bad at this! Translating into English is so tough!
We... are... going...
to... swimming... s-w-i-m-m-i-n-g...
のじゃ！
Noja!
プールにがない！
I didn't put "at the pool"!
We are going swimming at the pool.
なんで to ないの？なんで to ないのじゃ？
Why is there no "to"? Why is there no "to"?
Why? Why no "to"? Why no "to"?
-ing が重複？-ing... to -ing はだめ？
Are there duplicate "-ing"s? Is "to -ing" no good?
Why? Why... not bad と？
Why? "Not bad", you say?
We are going swimming at the pool.
to the pool or going swimming...
to the pool...
不定詞？to 不定詞？うわ、わかんない言葉きた！不定詞きた、不定詞！
Infinitives? To-infinitives? Whoa, a word I don't know! Infinitives came up!
We are going to swim...
going で ing を使うなら to swim？
If you use "-ing" with "going", is it "to swim"?
to があるなら swim？
If there's "to", is it "swim"?
to の後に ing がつかない？
You don't put "-ing" after "to"?
うーん、going to swim, going swimming at the place...
Hmm, "going to swim", "going swimming at the place"...
うーん、不定詞ってなんじゃ？
Hmm, what even is an infinitive?
To swim or swimming, not to swimming.
to... to はだめ。
"To"... "to" is no good.
be -ing to で未来形？
Is "be -ing to" the future tense?
be... be が are じゃろ？
"be"... "be" is "are", right?
-ing, going...
あ、to の後 swimming の時点でダメなのか。
Ah, having "swimming" after "to" is why it's wrong?
ほーほーほーほーほーほー...
Uh-huh, uh-huh, uh-huh...
be going to 動詞。
"be going to + verb."
be going to 動詞なのじゃ。
It's "be going to + verb."
going...
でも to が模範解答にないから、だめなのじゃ？
But since "to" isn't in the correct answer, that's why it's wrong?
To swim, what you will do.
Swimming, what you are doing.
あー...じゃあ...
Ah... Then...
じゃあ to swim でもいいの？
Then is "to swim" fine too?
Swimming, what you are doing. でも泳ぎ...およ...
"Swimming, what you are doing." But "oyogi"...
泳いでいる状態になる？
...Does it mean being in the state of swimming?
「go to swim」ならオッケー？
Is "go to swim" okay then?
「to swim」なら大丈夫。
"To swim" is fine.
We are going to swim...
「at the pool」でもオッケー？
Is "at the pool" okay too?
だったのか？
Was that it?
「go swimming」が泳ぎに行く。
"Go swimming" means going swimming.
「go to swim」が泳ぐために行く。
"Go to swim" means going in order to swim.
あ、意味が変わっちゃうのじゃ！
Ah, the meaning actually changes!
細かいニュアンスが変わっちゃうっぽい。
The subtle nuance seems to change.
どっちもオッケーだけど、
Both are okay, but...
なんかより良いニュアンスにするには、
to make it sound more natural,
going...
ん？「go swimming」？
Huh? "Go swimming"?
になるっぽい。
That seems to be it.
「go V-ing」が自然な表現。オッケー。
"Go V-ing" is the natural phrasing. Okay.
じゃあ、これは不自然な表現のじゃ。「going swimming」
Then this is an unnatural phrasing: "going swimming."
「go shopping」...
"Go shopping"...
オッケー。
Okay.
じゃあ、なんか「何々しに行きます」の場合は...
So in the case of "going to do something"...
でも正解例は「going swimming」じゃからな。
But Duolingo's correct answer was "going swimming."
えー、-ingが2回来るの不思議な感じするのじゃ。
Having "-ing" twice feels so strange!
不思議な感じするー。
It feels so weird.
ちょっとこれは、あのー、経験で何とかするしかないのじゃ。オッケー。
Well, I guess I'll just have to get used to it through experience. Okay.
「驚異の集中力！」次へ。
"Incredible focus!" Next.
え、でもパス？パスカモ、パス？
Wait, did I pass? Maybe I passed?
パスしたかも？
Maybe I passed?
パスしたかも！
I might have passed!
オッケーだったかものじゃ！
It might have been accepted!
ちょ、ちょ、なんかいっぱいある。
Wait, wait, there's so many pop-ups.
ロックされた？アンロックのじゃ？
Was it locked? Unlocked!
アンロックのじゃ？
Unlocked?
ちょっといっぱい出てくる。
Lots of things are popping up.
後で。
Later.
ん？セクション3にチャレンジ権がある！
Huh? I have the chance to challenge Section 3!
見て、you guys見て、ルックのじゃ！
Look, you guys, look! Look at this!
セクション3行ける！
I can go to Section 3!
やったー！
Yay!
やったのじゃ！
I did it!
なんか配信前の朝試したときは、
When I tried this morning before the stream,
あのー、ライフ0、最後の和訳のところで
my hearts hit zero on the last Japanese translation,
0じゃったんじゃが、
it went to zero, but...
合格したのじゃー！
I passed!
やったのじゃー！
Woohoo!
最初のingは未来を示して、
The first "-ing" indicates the future,
後のingは動名詞。出た、動名詞！
and the second "-ing" is a gerund. There it is, gerunds!
あの、わしが授業で聞いて全く分かんなかったやつ！
The thing I never understood at all when taught in class!
何？
What?
あの、ジャパニーズ...
Um, Japanese...
ジャパニーズ主らは動名詞とか理解してるのじゃ？
Do you Japanese folks understand gerunds?
授業で理解できたタイプ？
Were you the type who understood it in class?
わしは...
I...
分かんなかった。
never understood it.
わしは動名詞とかそういうの分かんなかったのじゃ。
I didn't understand gerunds or anything like that.
I can't understand 動名詞のじゃ。
I can't understand gerunds.
ちょっと待っててね。
Wait just a second.
覚えるぞ。覚えるのじゃ。
I'll memorize it. I'm gonna learn it.
これからね、学ぶのじゃ。
From now on, I will study.
わしと一緒に覚えるのじゃ。
Let's learn together with me.
雰囲気じゃなくてね、
Not just by gut feeling,
確実に覚えるのじゃ。
but properly memorize it.
オッケー。じゃあ、セクション3。「運動について話す」
Okay. So, Section 3: "Talk about exercise."
運動ってなんじゃ？スポーツ？
What is "exercise"? Sports?
Talk about sportsのじゃ。
"Talk about sports."
行くのじゃ！
Let's go!
のじゃ。
Alright.
Catch the ball.
音量オッケー？ちっちゃい？
Is the volume okay? Too quiet?
Catch
「Catch the ball」ボールを
"Catch the ball." The ball...
キャッチして
Catch...
オッケーのじゃ。
Okay!
Wow, you read fast!
Wow, you read fast.
わあ、
Wow,
あなたは
you...
読むのが
are fast...
速いよ。
at reading.
うん！オッケーのじゃ。
Yep! Okay!
That player always catches the ball.
Catches
そのプレイヤーは、いつもボールをキャッチする。
That player always catches the ball.
空振らない？空振らないのじゃ。
Never misses? Never misses a catch!
この辺はイージーのじゃ。
This part is easy!
I understand... I 何？理解できる。I can understand this.
I understand... I what? Can understand. I can understand this.
分かる。
I get it.
分かるけど、テスト難しかった。
I get it, but the test was hard.
Why do you always walk fast?
えっと、Why do you always...
Um, "Why do you always..."
Why do you always walk fast?
ファスト。
Fast.
なんでいつも早く歩くの？
Why do you always walk fast?
もっとゆっくり歩いてほしいのじゃ。
I want you to walk more slowly!
Writing sentences is the hardest part. Yes, そう。
"Writing sentences is the hardest part." Yes, exactly.
そう、I... I'm not good at... あの和訳...
Yeah, I... I'm not good at... Japanese translation...
ジャパニーズに…
Into Japanese...
イングリッシュ to ジャパニーズ？
English to Japanese?
ん？ノー。ジャパニーズ to イングリッシュができない。
Hm? No, I can't do Japanese to English.
そう、それができないのじゃ。
Right, that's what I can't do.
次。
Next.
空欄を埋めてください。I run fast, 早く走れます。
"Fill in the blank." "I run fast"—I can run fast.
She can run fast. 彼女も早く走れます。トム…
"She can run fast." She can run fast too. Tom...
Tom can surf.
なんか一人だけ違う。
Somehow, only one of them is different.
トムはドリブルが上手い！
Tom is good at dribbling!
いい感じ！
Looking good!
のじゃ。のじゃー。
Noja. Nojaaa.
なんで走りの話してるのにトムだけ… トムだけ… トムだけサーフの話？
Why are they talking about running, but only Tom... only Tom is talking about surfing?
Why, why トム surf? Why surf?
Why, why does Tom surf? Why surf?
何、のじゃ。
What's up with that?
次。
Next.
Yes, I can surf well.
トム来た！
Tom is here!
Yes, I can surf well.
Oh...
ん？
Hm?
fast, too
これ何？待って、これ分かんない。
What's this? Wait, I don't get this.
Yes, I can surf well.
私はあの、サーフィンがめっちゃ上手くできますよ。Oh…
"I, um, can surf really well." Oh...
heじゃないよね。
It wouldn't be "he", right?
can fast, too...
run fast, too...
早く走れやってこと？
Does it mean "Run fast!"?
あ！
Ah!
He can run fast, too.
あ、一個じゃないのか！Only oneじゃと思った！
Ah, it's not just one word! I thought it was only one!
なるほど！
I see!
Yes, I can surf well. Oh, he can run fast, too.
サーフィンもできるし、早く走ることもできますよってことか。
So it's "I can surf, and he can run fast too"!
オッケー、オッケー。I thought… 1個、1個だと思った。あの、only oneじゃと思った、選択するの。
Okay, okay. I thought... I thought it was just one word to choose.
3つね！オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Three words! Okay, okay, okay.
がっといっと。
Got it.
He can run very fast.
めっちゃ早く走れる。
He can run super fast.
足が速い。オッケー。
He's fast on his feet. Okay.
Junior can run fast.
さすがに走るんじゃない？
Surely it's "run", right?
ジュニアも早く走れる。
Junior can run fast too.
足早が多いのじゃ。
There are so many fast runners.
many... many fast run people.
Many... many fast running people.
人間。ヒューマン。うん。
Humans. Humans. Yeah.
Mela can run very fast?
メラは… lateかな。
Mela is... late, maybe.
メラは… メラはちょっとlate。
Mela is... Mela is a bit late.
ねぇ、サラマンダーよりずっと早いてちょっと切ないやつってわし知ってるのじゃ。
Hey, I know a rather bittersweet story about someone being way faster than a salamander.
のじゃ！
Noja!
Yes, Anna can run very fast.
アンナはめっちゃ早く走れる。
Anna can run super fast.
Yes, Ben can swim well.
ベンは泳ぐのが上手い。
Ben is good at swimming.
What is this? 何この会話、何、何この会話？
What is this? What is this conversation? What even is this?
早く走れる、泳ぎも上手いぜ、のじゃ？
"She can run fast." "He can swim well too", noja?
What is this, のじゃ？
What is this, noja?
うーん。
Hmm.
オッケー。
Okay.
I can surf.
サーフィンできるのじゃ。サーフィンしたことないのじゃ。
I can surf, noja. Though I've never surfed before.
Yes, I can swim.
Yes, I can swim. はい。
"Yes, I can swim." Yes.
泳げます。
"I can swim."
泳げます！
I can swim!
My mom can swim.
パターンだから会話ではない。あ、なるほどのじゃ。パターンなのじゃ？会話じゃないのじゃ。
It's sentence patterns, not a conversation. Ah, I see! Patterns, noja? It's not a conversation.
Mom...
My mom can swim.
「私の母は泳げる。」
"My mother can swim."
My momはどうかの？泳げるかの？My mom can swim? 知らないのじゃ。
How about my mom? Can she swim? "My mom can swim?" I don't know!
メラは… あのー… I'm not good at water, swimming. Because my...
Mela is... um... I'm not good at water, swimming. Because my...
見て、水… hairからさ、my hairからさ、わさ burningじゃからさ。
Look, water... from my hair, from my hair, it's burning, you know?
見て、炎。炎あるのじゃ。Fireあるから…
Look, flames. There are flames. Because there is fire...
あの、犬かきならできるのじゃ。犬かきってこれ何じゃ？調べよう。
Um, I can do the dog paddle. What is dog paddle in English? Let me check.
犬かき… 犬かき…
Dog paddle... dog paddle...
うんと、I can do じゃ dog paddle.
Um, "I can do dog paddle".
dog paddle
うん。
Yeah.
犬かきで泳げる。I can swim dog paddle swimming できるのじゃ。うん。
I can swim dog paddle. "I can swim"—I can do dog paddle swimming, noja. Yeah.
シャワーのときは火消すのじゃ。のじゃ。うん。
When I take a shower, I put out the fire. Noja. Yeah.
でもなんか、あの…
But somehow, um...
クロールとか普通の泳ぎは苦手 平泳ぎとか
I'm not good at regular swimming like the crawl stroke, breaststroke and...
そういうのはできないのじゃ
...things like that, I can't do, noja.
うん
Yeah.
独特のやつのみできるのじゃ
I can only do my own unique way, noja.
うん のじゃ
Yeah. Noja.
お風呂入っているのじゃ
I do take baths, noja.
お風呂入る時は火消すのじゃ
When I take a bath, I put out the fire, noja.
あの わしのね 髪の毛の火とね どうなってるか知りたい人はね
Um, for those who want to know what's up with the fire in my hair,
昨日投稿した自己紹介動画をね 見るとね
if you watch the self-introduction video I posted yesterday,
解明される気がしますのじゃ
I feel like it'll be cleared up, noja.
ぜひ見てほしいのじゃ
I'd really like you to watch it, noja.
次
Next.
He never drives fast.
え 彼は...
Uh, 'He'...
neverだから...
Since it's 'never'...
彼は 全く...「決して」かな？
He, 'not at all'... or 'never'?
決して 早く 運転 しない
'Never' 'drives' 'fast'.
never... neverってなんじゃ？全く？
Never... What is 'never', noja? 'Not at all'?
全くか
Maybe 'not at all'?
全く早く運転しない
'He doesn't drive fast at all.'
「決して」じゃった！
It was 'never'!
別の表現で...あ 何でもいいんじゃな
Another phrasing... Oh, either is fine, then.
何でもいいんじゃな ふんふんふん
Either is fine, noja. I see, I see.
Yes, yesterday's self-introduce video
Yes, 'Yesterday's self-intro video...
had more about the fire in my hair?
...had more about the fire in your hair?'
So watch... watch that!
So I said that.
That's what I said.
うん どっちもOK
Yeah, both are okay.
He never drives fast.
They can run fast.
なんか 走る速さが
Like, how fast you run...
あの 序列に繋がってそうな場所...
...seems to be linked to your social hierarchy...
速く走れたらモテる的な小学生価値観のじゃ
That elementary school mindset where running fast makes you popular, noja.
いい調子 OK？
'Good job.' Okay?
ふんふんふん
Mhm, mhm.
Are there English translation on that video? あっ
'Are there English translations on that video?' Ah,
Not yet!
えっ 聞いてみよう
Eh, let me ask!
いつか付けられるように...
So they can be added someday...
I try to take English translation.
I'll try to get English translations.
Wait for it.
待ってほしいのじゃ
Please wait for it, noja.
えっ メモしとこう 忘れないように
Eh, let me make a note so I don't forget.
待って...付けたい ちょっと待ってね
Wait... I want to add them. Hold on a second.
手元にメモがあるから書くのじゃ
I have a notepad here, so I'll write it down, noja.
えーっと 自己紹介...
Umm... Self-introduction...
イングリッシュ トランス...
...English trans...
...レーション OK
...lation. Okay.
OK I try it, noja!
Okay. 'I will try it, noja!'
Wait, noja!
OK
Okay.
えー 彼はとても速く走れる He...
Uh, 'He can run very fast.' He...
...can run very fast.
うん
Yep.
ボールをキャッチできるよね？
'You can catch the ball, right?'
あー... Can you...
Ah... Can you...
...catch a ball?
あ 「right」もいるの？なくてもいいらしい
Ah, does it need 'right' too? Seems it's okay without it.
「よね？」 I, I remember!
'Right?' I, I remember!
覚えてるよ！覚えてるのじゃ！
I remember! I remember, noja!
Achichii Mela is cute, right?
覚えてる！I, I know, I know! 知ってるのじゃ！
I remember! I, I know, I know! I know, noja!
知ってるのじゃ！
I know, noja!
知ってるのじゃ！Remember, right? Yes, yes, yes, yes!
I know, noja! Remember, right? Yes, yes, yes, yes!
やったやったやったやったやった！のじゃ！
Yay, yay, yay, yay, yay! Noja!
わかるのじゃ！Yes.
I understand, noja! Yes.
Okay, you guys!
Achichii Mela is so cute, right?
Right?
うん うん うん うん うん
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
うん うん うん うん のじゃ！
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah, noja!
Yes! Achichii Mela is pretty cute,
right?
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes! Okay, I...
覚えてる！覚えてるのじゃ！Remember! Remember, noja!
I remember! I remember, noja! Remember! Remember, noja!
のじゃ！
Noja!
えー トムはボールをとても上手にキャッチできる
Uh, 'Tom can catch a ball very well.'
Tom can catch a ball
very well.
のじゃ！
Noja!
うん Yes, yes, yes.
Yep. Yes, yes, yes.
やったー！クリアーのじゃーー！
Yay! Cleared, noja!
OK！のじゃー！
Okay! Noja!
ん？運動について話す...スポーツについて話す？
Hm? 'Talk about exercise'... Talking about sports?
ボールを...蹴る...蹴れ？
'Ball'... 'kick'... 'Kick it'?
蹴れ？ボールを蹴れ！
'Kick it'? 'Kick the ball!'
のじゃーーん！
Nojaa!
Don't kick my chair!
嫌な奴！椅子蹴るのダメ！
What a jerk! Don't kick the chair!
椅子...
Chair...
蹴るのはダメ
Kicking is not allowed.
You guys don't kick chair.
あのー、シアターとかで
Like at the theater...
映画館とかでさ
or movie cinemas, you know...
チェ、チェアをさ、蹴る人がいる。
Some people kick the ch- chair.
やだ。
I hate that.
やだー！
I hate it!
蹴らないでー！
Don't kick it!
Don't kick my chair!
やだのじゃー！
I really hate that!
うーん、うん、うん、うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, mm-hmm...
そう、that's rude. そう、not、not。
Right, that's rude. Yeah, not cool, not cool.
ダメ、嫌なやつ。
Not good. Such annoying people.
だから一番後ろに座る対策のじゃ。
That's why my strategy is to sit in the very back!
うーん。
Yeah.
I will push your chair instead.
押さなくていいよ。
You don't need to push it either.
ドント・プッシュ。
Don't push.
押さなくてもいいのじゃ。
You don't have to push it either!
オッケー？
Okay?
Throw the ball.
Throw the ball. ボールを投げて。
"Throw the ball." Throw the ball.
冒頭に動詞が来て、びっくりとかがつく時は命令形って聞いたのじゃ。
I heard that when a verb comes first with an exclamation mark, it's an imperative.
命令形。
Imperative form.
命令。
An order.
うん、Emma swims every day. エマは毎日泳ぎます。
Okay, "Emma swims every day." Emma swims every day.
Max can't swim. マックスは泳げません。
"Max can't swim." Max can't swim.
He can't...
What? "play" or "plays"?
play!
in the water.
なんでだろう？確かに、な、どういう時に「s」つくんじゃ？
Why is that? When does "-s" actually get added?
なんか、"He plays" とか...
Like, "He plays" or something...
なんか、can't がなかったら...
Like, if there was no "can't"...
can't がなかったら、I think 「s」だと思うんじゃが、
If there was no "can't", I think there'd be an "-s", but...
引っかけ？
Is it a trick?
can't の後に、after can't, no "s". あ！
After "can't"... after "can't", no "-s". Ah!
I know! 知ってた！
I know! I knew it!
Knew! I knew, I knew!
知ってたのじゃ、知ってたのじゃ！三人称単数、can't がある。あ！
I knew it, I knew it! Third person singular, but there's "can't". Ah!
なるほどー。
I see.
can の後は「no」なんだ。
After "can", it's "no [s]".
「助動詞の後は原形」助動詞ってなんじゃ？
"Base form follows auxiliary verbs." What's an auxiliary verb?
What is 助動詞？
What is an auxiliary verb?
助動詞って何？
What's an auxiliary verb?
助動詞ってどれ？can't?
Which one is the auxiliary verb? "can't"?
can't is 助動詞？
Is "can't" an auxiliary verb?
大惨事は違うのじゃ！
"Great disaster" is wrong!
ん？can は助動詞？あ、can が助動詞。
Huh? "can" is an auxiliary verb? Ah, "can" is the auxiliary verb.
動詞の原形、にょー。
Base form of the verb, nyaow~
can't とか will ってのが助動詞。can't と will。
Things like "can't" and "will" are auxiliary verbs. "can't" and "will".
へー、のじゃー。
Huh, I see.
うーん。
Hmm.
Yes, can is auxiliary verb.
Auxiliary verb, 助動詞。
"Auxiliary verb," jodoushi.
うーん。
Hmm.
オッケー、オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
うーん。
Hmm.
え、じゃあ、あの無意識のうちに文法を理解していた
Wait, so without even realizing it, I understood grammar...
わし。
...little old me.
なぜか選べた、play がちゃんと選べた
Somehow I was able to choose it, I properly chose "play"...
わし。
...little old me.
麻雀知ってる口なのじゃ。ちょっとだけわかる。ちょっと。
It's like I know mahjong! I get it just a bit. Just a bit.
あれ、わかるのじゃ。
See? I understand.
She can throw and catch very well.
オッケー。
Okay.
She can throw and catch very well.
めっちゃ上手に投げたり捕ったりできるのじゃ。
She can throw and catch super well!
She can't throw a ball.
彼女はボールを投げられないのじゃ。
She cannot throw a ball!
She throws the ball far.
遠くにボールを投げれます。
She can throw the ball far.
遠くにボールを、ん？違うな。can じゃない。
Throw the ball far... Huh? Wait, no. Not "can".
She throws the ball far. 彼女は遠くにボールを投げます。
"She throws the ball far." She throws the ball far.
彼女は遠くにボールを投げれます。
She can throw the ball far.
Lisa can throw the ball far.
見て！can、あの助動詞の後は「s」つかない！
Look! After "can", that auxiliary verb, there's no "-s"!
助動詞の後は「s」つかない！
After an auxiliary verb, there's no "-s"!
うん。
Yeah.
This is showing you when use, when to use the "s".
確かに！
True!
far
確かに！
Indeed!
She throws, throws, the ball far.
can がないね。
There's no "can", right.
She can throw, 「s」がない、no "s"!
"She can throw," there's no "-s", no "-s"!
Lisa can throw the ball far.
can だから「s」無いのじゃ。
Because of "can", there is no "-s"!
オッケー。
Okay.
遠い、far。
Far, "far".
far
遠いのじゃ。
It means "far"!
Ben, can you kick this ball?
ball
このボールを蹴れますか？
Can you kick this ball?
I can't swim.
泳げませんのじゃ。
I cannot swim!
Is Tom good at football?
Yes, he makes really great cakes. Cakes! Not cakes!
No, he can't throw a ball very far.
フットボールって...
With football...
投げるの？
do they throw it?
フットボールって投げるの？
Do you throw the ball in football?
フットボールってさ...
I mean, with football...
Football.
ハンド？
With hands?
あ、アメリカンフットボール！
Ah, American football!
アメリカンフットボール！オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
American football! Okay, okay, okay.
分かった、分かった、分かった。
I get it, I get it now.
のじゃ？
Right, noja?
アメリカンフットボールね。オッケー、オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
American football, I see. Okay, okay, okay, okay.
Your なんちゃら...
Your, something...
can kick the ball very far, right? Your...
neighbor かな？
neighbor, maybe?
Neighbor.
ポテトじゃないし、シャンプーでもないし。
It's not potato, nor shampoo.
あなたの隣人は...
Your neighbor...
遠くにボールを蹴れます。
can kick the ball far,
のじゃ。
noja.
オッケー！
Okay!
Why are you good at soccer?
Why are you good at soccer? なんでサッカーそんな上手なの？
Why are you good at soccer? Why are you so good at soccer?
I don't have my wallet right now. What?
I can kick a ball very far.
これ答えになってないのじゃ？
Isn't this an answer, noja?
Why are you good at soccer?
なんでそんな... あ、答えになってるか。「なんで上手なん？」
Why are you so... Ah, it is an answer. "Why are you good?"
「ボール遠くに蹴れるから」なのじゃ。
"Because I can kick the ball far", noja.
まあ、まあ、まあか。
Well, I suppose so.
まあか。
I guess.
まあ、まあ、まあ。
Well, fair enough.
まあオッケーか。
I guess that works.
うん。
Yeah.
This question is too weird. Yes, I think so too.
I think so too!
I can't run very far.
えーっと...
Let's see...
遠くまであまり...
Not really far away...
I can't run very far.
えー、あまり遠くまで走れない。
Uh, "I can't run very far."
のじゃ。
Noja.
いい調子。オッケー！
Looking good. Okay!
Why are you so cute, noja?
なんでじゃと思う？ Because you guys...
Why do you think, noja? Because you guys...
tell me cute many, a lot.
You guys tell me cute,
You guys tell me I'm cute,
so I am cute, noja!
のじゃー！
Noja!
Yes, because you said "cute" to me.
オッケー？
Okay?
ん。
Yeah.
のじゃー。
Noja.
えーっと、I can...
Um, I can...
kick the ball...
very がない。too... too は違う。
There's no "very". Too... "too" is wrong.
Too far って言わなくない？
Wouldn't you NOT say "too far"?
Too far って聞かない。
I never hear "too far".
なんでだ？
Why is that?
なんでじゃ？ Too far 聞いたことない。
Why, noja? I've never heard "too far".
のじゃ。
Noja.
聞いたことない。なんでじゃろう？
I've never heard it. I wonder why?
very far 言うけど
They say "very far", but...
Too far 聞いたことないよ。
I've never heard "too far".
なんでじゃ？
Why, noja?
なんか聞いたことあるかないかで英語を判断している。
I'm judging English by whether I've heard it or not.
うーん...
Hmm...
Too だとちょっとネガティブなニュアンス？
Does "too" have a somewhat negative nuance?
遠すぎる。Too far is... 遅すぎる？
"Too far". "Too far" is... too late?
うーん、遠すぎる。
Hmm, too far away.
Too は「すぎる」？うーん。
Does "too" mean "excessively"? Hmm.
遠すぎ。
Too far.
「すぎる」。うーん。
"Excessively"... hmm.
じゃあ遠くへじゃないのか。うーん。
Then does it not mean "to a far distance"? Hmm.
Too far, 遠すぎる。
Too far, "too far".
ほお、限界を超えている。
Oh, "exceeding the limit".
のーじゃ。
Noja.
よくない、Too far is not good.
Not good. "Too far" is not good.
オッケー、オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
ニュアンスが変わっちゃうのじゃ。
The nuance ends up changing, noja.
なるほどなのじゃ。
I see, noja.
ほおー。
I see.
コメントは... あ、でも、but
The comments are... Ah, but...
あの問題を解く時、when I uh...
Um, when I'm solving a problem, when I, uh...
question, when I answer question,
question, when I answer a question,
I don't watch comments.
I don't look at comments.
So I, after I answer the question,
I watch comment.
I look at comments.
チャット？うん。After I answer だから、
Chat? Yeah. Since it's after I answer,
あの、you guys は
um, you guys...
えーっと、オッケー。書いていいよ。
um, it's okay. You can write them.
書いていいのじゃ。
You can write them, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
スポイラー？うん。
Spoilers? Yeah.
オッケーのじゃ。
It's fine, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
Only I answer...
Only [when] I answer...
ん？
Hm?
I don't watch chat
I don't look at chat
when I answer question.
when I answer the question.
オッケー。
Okay.
Okay, no cheating, okay?
うん。
Yeah.
オッケーのじゃ
All righty, then!
から you guys、あの...
So you guys, um...
can write と answer in チャット
can write the answers in the chat.
うん
Yeah.
書いていいよ because I don't watch
You can write them, because I don't look.
うん
Yep.
のじゃ
Noja.
オッケー
Okay.
次！
Next!
サッカーボールが蹴れない！
"I can't kick a soccer ball!"
I
can't
kick
ボールがない
There's no "ball".
あ、ボールあった
Ah, there it is.
I can't kick a soccer...
...ball
うん
Yeah.
彼女はボールが投げられない
"She can't throw a ball."
She can't
throw
a
ball
オッケー
Okay.
グレートのじゃー！
Great, noja!
パーフェクトのじゃー！
Perfect, noja!
オッケー
Okay.
オッケー、運動について話すー
Okay, "talking about exercise"...
で、more
And "more".
オッケー
Okay.
ん？
Hm?
Football? This Duolingo is so wrong!
Not soccer? Football? フットボール？
Not soccer? Football? Football?
さっきの問題が the ball だったのがモヤる
It bugs me that the last question had "the ball".
なんで？なんで？なんで？
Why? Why? Why?
the ball じゃなくて a ball なのじゃ？
Why is it "a ball" instead of "the ball", noja?
わし a と the の違いがあんまり分かってないのじゃ
I don't really get the difference between "a" and "the", noja.
It's soccer. Football yes.
これ派閥か？
Is this a feud?
Is there a feud over this?
オッケー？
Okay?
"Soccer is American only" あ、オッケー
"Soccer is American only." Ah, okay.
なんかコメント欄でも荒れてる
People are arguing in the comments too.
チャット欄でも
In the chat, too.
これアメリカ英語？
Is this American English?
It's American English.
なるほどね
I see.
は、派閥があるのね
S-so there really are factions.
あんま、あんま触れなきゃよかった？
Should I, should I not have brought it up?
あんま触れない方がいいやつのじゃ？
Is that something I shouldn't touch on, noja?
うーん...
Hmm...
オケオケオケオケ
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
なんかあるのね
So there really is a divide.
どっちかみたいのがあって
There's two sides to it,
Duolingo はあの、サッカーのやつ？
and Duolingo is the "soccer" camp?
"Japan calls it soccer, too." Yes.
ジャパンも、ジャパンでものじゃ
Japan too, in Japan as well, noja.
あ、ひ、火の用心じゃ！火の用心じゃ！
Ah, fi- beware of fire! Beware of fire!
のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ！
Noja, noja, noja!
無知は、無知は争いを生みますのじゃー！
Ignorance, ignorance breeds conflict, noja!
のじゃーー
Nojaaa!
なるほど、あの、きのこたけのこ的な感じのじゃ？
I see, so it's like the Mushroom Mountain vs. Bamboo Village thing, noja?
のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ
Noja, noja, noja.
いやー、やはりね
Well, really, you know,
あの、炎上はいかにして起こるかっていう話なんじゃが
when it comes to how internet fires start,
無知なのじゃ、ズバリ
it's ignorance, pure and simple.
悪意のない炎上というのは無知によって起こりますのじゃ
Dramas born without malice happen because of ignorance, noja.
うん
Yeah.
知らないということは罪ですのじゃ
Not knowing is a sin, noja.
あの、知らないことは実は罪ではそんなないんじゃが
Well, not knowing in itself isn't really that sinful,
表に出て、配信をしたり発信活動をする人間が
but for someone who puts themselves out there streaming and creating content
知らないというのは、なかなかにギルティですのじゃー！
to not know is quite guilty, nojaaa!
火の用心じゃーー！
Beware of fireee!
オッケー、オッケーのじゃ
Okay, okay noja.
オッケー、オッケー、オッケー...
Okay, okay, okay...
"Be careful for fire." オッケー、オッケー
"Be careful for fire." Okay, okay.
Be careful, be careful のじゃー！
Be careful, be careful, nojaaa!
のじゃ、Fire Safety First のじゃー
Noja, "Fire Safety First", noja.
オッケー
Okay.
のじゃ
Noja.
よし、じゃ「重り」、「重り」選ぶのじゃ！
All right, then let's choose "weights", "weights", noja!
ネクスト！ネクストのじゃーー！
Next! Next, nojaaa!
「ちなみにメラちゃんたけのこの里派ですか？」
"By the way, Mela-chan, are you team Takenoko?"
燃やそうとすな！燃やそうとすな！
Don't try to start a fire! Don't start a fire!
わしの配信を、わしの配信を燃やそうとすな！
Don't try to set my stream on fire!
のじゃ！weight
Noja! Weight.
weight のじゃ
"Weight", noja.
うん
Yeah.
あの、お答えすることは避けますのじゃ
Um, I will refrain from answering, noja.
明言は、明言することは避けさせていただきますのじゃ
I will, I will refrain from making any definite statement, noja.
あのー...
Um...
何も言わない沈黙ですのじゃ
I'll say nothing and maintain silence, noja.
賢い、賢いわしは沈黙を選択いたしますのじゃ
Wise, clever as I am, I choose silence, noja.
うん
Yep.
わしのコメント欄に放火魔がおりますのじゃー！
There's an arsonist in my comment section, nojaaa!
はぁ、恐ろしいのじゃー
Haah, terrifying, noja.
恐ろしいのじゃー
Terrifying, noja.
Do you also have weights at home?
Okay, uh, do you also have weights at home?
「重りが家にありますか？」
"Do you have weights at home?"
ないのじゃ、no, no のじゃ、no のじゃ、no のじゃ
I don't, noja. No, no, noja. No, noja. No, noja.
答えは沈黙！
The answer is silence!
Yes, クラピカも言ってたのじゃ！
Yes, Kurapika said it too, noja!
沈黙が正しいですのじゃ
Silence is the right answer, noja.
うん
Yeah.
ハンター試験クリアさせていただきますのじゃ
I shall now pass the Hunter Exam, noja.
A heavy bag
A heavy bag, 重いカバン
A heavy bag, "a heavy bag".
うん
Yeah.
These weights are heavy.
重りヘビーじゃなかったらあんま意味ないのじゃ
If weights aren't heavy, there's not much point to them, noja.
Can he lift those weights?
Can you- Can he lift those weights?
Can you— Can he lift those weights?
「リフト」って何？
What does "lift" mean?
Can he lift those weights... 持ち上げられるとかかな？
"Can he lift those weights"... maybe like "lift up"?
持ち上げます。んー...
"To lift up." Hmm...
Can she play basketball, too?
オッケー。
Okay.
ふんふん。「リフト」が持ち上げる。
Mm-hm. "Lift" means to lift up.
「リフト」が持ち上げる。んー...
"Lift" means to lift up. Hmm...
リフティング！リフティングって言うよね？
Lifting! People say "lifting", right?
あの、サッカー、もしくはフットボールの、
Like in soccer, or football...
あの、あの... さ、ずっとボール浮かすやつ。
you know... keeping the ball in the air.
あれリフティングって言う？あれがあげる？
Is that lifting? Does that mean lifting it?
んーー...
Hmm...
やばい、「もしくは」って言ったのに「サッカー」って言われてる！
Even though I said "or", they're saying soccer!
「もしくは」って言ったのに！「もしくは」つったの！
Even though I said "or"! I said "or"!
あ、I said もしくは! I said OR! I said OR!
Ah, I said "or"! I said OR! I said OR!
言った！I said OR 言ったのじゃ！オッケー？
I said it! I said OR, noja! Okay?
んー... 怖い、怖い。炎上怖いのじゃー。オッケー？
Scary, scary. Backlash is scary, noja! Okay?
オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。
Okay, okay, okay.
I said OR. オッケー？
I said OR. Okay?
Yes. うん。オッケー。
Yes. Yeah. Okay.
Can Lisa surf well?
リサは上手にサーフィンができますか？
Do you lift weights at the gym?
ジムで重りを持ち上げますか？
Can you do a push-up?
Can you do a push-up? What is push-up?
Can you do a push-up? What is a push-up?
押してあげる...
Push and lift...
なんか、ジ、ジムのやつなのかな？筋トレのやつなのかな？
Is it, like, a gym thing? A workout thing?
Can you throw a ball?
ん、メラは、メラは、メラは筋トレしない。
M-Mela doesn't... Mela doesn't work out.
Do you lift, bro?
I'm not lift. 筋トレしない。
I'm not lift. I don't work out.
腕立て伏せ。Push-up is a gym exercise.
Push-ups. A push-up is a gym exercise.
へえー。ジムの話。
I see. Gym talk.
オッケー。プッシュアップ、腕立て伏せ。
Okay. Push-up is udetatefuse.
I, I can't push-up because it's hard.
I, I can't do push-ups because it's hard.
難しいからしない。うん。
It's hard so I don't do them. Yeah.
Actually, I go gym, but I only walking.
Actually, I go to the gym, but I only walk.
ウォーキングしかしないのじゃ。うん。
I only do walking, noja. Yeah.
ウォーキング。Just walking のじゃ。
Walking. Just walking, noja.
腕立て伏せ？Not even one push-up?
Push-ups? Not even one push-up?
If anyone say me...
If someone tells me...
「Do!」『しろ』って言われたらするけど、
"Do!" If they tell me to, I will, but...
自主的にはしないのじゃ。
I won't do it voluntarily, noja.
Because it's hard, too hard. ハードワーク。
Because it's hard, too hard. Hard work.
I don't like ハードワークのじゃ。うん。
I don't like hard work, noja. Yeah.
「How many miles do you walk?」
"How many miles do you walk?"
えー、マイル？マイルわかんないのじゃ。
Huh, miles? I don't know miles, noja.
あの、キロメーターでもいい？キロメーターでもいい？
Um, is kilometers okay? Can I use kilometers?
あの、5キロメーターぐらい歩くのじゃ。
Um, I walk about 5 kilometers, noja.
うん。キロメーターぐらい歩く。のじゃ。
Yeah. I walk that many kilometers, noja.
マイルがわかんない。
I don't know miles.
1.6？1.6キロメーターが1マイル。
1.6? 1.6 kilometers is 1 mile.
じゃあ、大体 around 5マイル...
Then roughly... around 5 miles...
ん？3... 3.1マイル？
Hm? 3... 3.1 miles?
3.1マイル！
3.1 miles!
ぐらい歩く。
I walk about that much.
のじゃ。
Noja.
うん。のじゃ。
Yeah. Noja.
あとジム、のじゃ。
And at the gym, noja.
Wow! Wow, can she do fifty push-ups?
50回も腕立て伏せできるのじゃ？
She can do 50 push-ups, noja?!
すごーい！それすごいのじゃ。
Amazing! That's incredible, noja.
I can't do push-ups.
Yes! これ、This is me! This is me!
Yes! This... This is me! This is me!
I can't do push-ups. できない。
"I can't do push-ups." I can't do them.
えーっと...
Ummm...
「腕立て伏せができない」
"I cannot do push-ups."
I can't because it's hard.
I can do five push-ups.
5回... ま、5回なら...
Five times... Well, if it's five times...
Maybe I can do five. Maybe. うん。
Maybe I can do five. Maybe. Yeah.
多分。Maybe ね。うん。
Probably. Maybe, right? Yeah.
Can you swim?
Push-ups are hard.
Yes! I think so too. プッシュアップ...
Yes! I think so too. Push-up...
プッシュアップス are hard.
Push-ups are hard.
「アップス」なんじゃね？
It's "ups", isn't it?
プッシュアップが1回じゃから、何回もやるとアップスになるんじゃね？
One is push-up, so multiple times makes it push-ups?
何回もあって、sになるから「are」なの？
Plural with an "s", so that's why it's "are"?
「腕立て伏せはきつい」Yes. 腕立...
"Push-ups are tough." Yes. Push-...
きつい
Tough.
Yes.
マルチプル...
Multiple...
Tom can do...
twenty...
push-ups.
20回。トム、20回。
20 times. Tom, 20 times.
オッケー。
Okay.
Push ups are hard. Yes, I think so too.
プッシュアップ名詞？プッシュアップ名詞なの？
Is push-up a noun? Push-up is a noun?
腹筋ない。ノー腹筋。
No abs. No abs.
プッシュアップっていう名詞だからs？
Because push-up is a noun, it gets an "s"?
名詞だからs？名詞だからsってなんじゃ？それ知らない。
Because it's a noun, "s"? What does that mean? I don't know that.
腕立て伏せができない。I...
"I cannot do push-ups." I...
can't...
do...
push...
ups.
わあ、Wow...
Whoa, "Wow"...
these...
weights are...
heavy.
ジムでウェイトをあげてますか？
"Do you lift weights at the gym?"
Are you...? 違うか。
"Are you...?" Or maybe not.
上げるが動詞だから、Doなのかな？
Since "lift" is a verb, maybe it's "Do"?
Do you...
lift... Do you lift...
weights...
at...
Do you lift the weights at...?
Do you lift weights at the gym?
どう？
How's that?
合ってる！？なんで合ってるかわかんない！Why!? Why!?
It's right!? I don't know why it's right! Why!? Why!?
なんで合ってるかわかんない！Why it is correct!?
I don't know why it's right! Why is it correct!?
わかんない！
I don't get it!
なんか適当にやったら合ってた！
I just randomly guessed and got it right!
適当にやったら合ってたのじゃ。
I guessed randomly and it worked out.
Do you lift weights...
リフトが上げる、ウェイトを上げる...
"Lift" means to raise, lifting weights...
Plural so no 'the' necessary?
weights... あ、sがあるからtheがいらない？
weights... Ah, because it has an "s", it doesn't need "the"?
You don't need to specify the object of the action.
Plural no 'the'... 複数形じゃない、weights.
"Plural no 'the'..." Isn't it plural, weights?
特定の重みじゃない...
It's not a specific weight...
It's not specific weights. It's weight in general.
確かに！ウェイトが... 'the weights'だったら...
True! If weight were... if it were "the weights"...
重みが限定されてる... かも。
...the weights would be specified... maybe.
ウェイトにこだわりがない、確かに。
There's no specific weight intended, that's true.
Weight lifting, lift weights, any weights...
確かに！Any weightsだ！Any weightsだからtheがいらない。
True! It's "any weights"! Because it's any weights, you don't need "the."
Lift the weights, the weights... both okay, but at gym is wrong, at the gym is right.
Why? Why 'at the gym' is right? なんで'at gym'がwrong?
Why? Why is "at the gym" right? Why is "at gym" wrong?
なんで... あの、そう、こっちもよく分かんない。'at gym'はダメ？
Why... like, yeah, I don't really get this part either. "at gym" is no good?
Why? なんで？
Why? Why is that?
なんで'at the'なの？'at gym'はノー？Why?
Why is it "at the"? "at gym" is a no? Why?
なんで...
Why...
The gym is a place?
The gym is... あ、'the gym'で1個なの？
"The gym is..." Ah, does "the gym" count as one thing?
It's a specific gym. 確かに。
"It's a specific gym." Indeed.
'Gym needs to be specific.' 確かに！
"Gym needs to be specific." Exactly!
ジムはどのジムかわかんない... どの... 確かに。
You don't know which gym it is... Which... true.
どのジムかわかんないとダメかも。
Maybe you have to know which gym it is.
The gym is specific place, at the gym is right. 確かに！
"The gym is a specific place, at the gym is right." Indeed!
確かに。そっか、じゃあ'the'を入れるところは...
True. I see, then where you put "the"...
指定しなきゃいけないとこ、
...is places that need to be specified.
指定しなきゃいけないとこは'the'がある。
Places that must be specified get a "the."
どのジムかわかんないと'a'でもいい？
If you don't know which gym, is "a" okay too?
え、ちなみに'a'と'the'の違いって何？
Wait, by the way, what's the difference between "a" and "the"?
What is the... the difference of 'the' と 'a'?
What is the... the difference between "the" and "a"?
'the gym' and 'a gym'がオッケー。オッケー、オッケー、オッケー。あ、わかってきた。
"the gym" and "a gym" are both okay. Okay, okay, okay. Ah, I'm starting to get it.
'a' is one among many.
'the' is specific one. ああー！
"the" is a specific one. Ahh!
じゃあ、本当にさっき言った通りだ。
Then it's really just like we said earlier.
何でもいい時は'a'。よくわかんない時は'a'？
When it can be anything, it's "a." When you don't know, it's "a"?
よくわかんない時は'a'だけど、'at a gym'...
When you don't know, it's "a", but "at a gym"...
んだけど...
But...
なんか、きっと何のジムかわかってるんじゃないの？
Like, they surely already know which gym it is, right?
何のジムかわかってると the gym
If they know which gym it is, it's "the gym"?
the... specific... specific...
「あの」specific
"That" specific.
どっかのジムに行く... ふーん...
Going to some gym... Hmm...
いろんなジムに行くなら、あ、OK。many many gymに...
If you go to various gyms... Ah, okay. If you go to many, many gyms...
行くなら a。
...then "a".
the「あの」、a「何か」？
"The" is "that", "a" is "any"?
うーん... あのジム。
Hmm... That gym.
じゃあ、the の方が... 使う？
Then would "the" be used more?
「その」とかがついてたら the。
If it has "that" or something, it's "the".
Mastering article is super important for English.
"Mastering articles is super important for English."
I think so too. でも、あんまりよく分かんない。
I think so too. But I don't really get it.
ランダムなチョコザップなら a。なるほど。
If it's a random Chocozap, it's "a". I see.
ランダムなチョコザップなら a だけど、チョコザップ〇〇店なら the。
A random Chocozap is "a", but Chocozap [location] is "the".
ほーん... the で特定。
Ooh... Specified with "the".
I go to a gym on the weekend.
You don't specify which gym. 確かに。
"You don't specify which gym." True.
じゃあ、あんまり仲良くない人には a？
Then would it be "a" for someone you're not close with?
あんまり仲良くない... あの、知らない人には a。
For people you're not close with... strangers, it's "a".
うーん... ふんふんふんふん。
Hmm... Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
ほーーん...
Hoo...
Exactly depends on how specific you're in the situation. 確かに。
"Exactly, depends on how specific you are in the situation." True.
確かに。
Indeed.
ふーん...
Hmm...
both OK。
Both are okay.
へー...
Huh...
I go to the gym, the other person understands which gym you are talking about と。
"'I go to the gym', the other person understands which gym you're talking about, huh?
あー... I go to the gym。
Ah... "I go to the gym."
じゃあ、な、仲良い...
Then to... close...
遊びまわりたいメンバーに「I go to the gym」っていうのは丸じゃけど...
saying "I go to the gym" to friends you hang out with is fine, but...
例えば、you guys？ メラ組 don't know...
For example, you guys? Melagumi don't know...
where... what gym I go じゃん？
where... what gym I go to, right?
メラ組は、わしがどのジムに行くか知らないじゃろ？
Melagumi doesn't know which gym I go to, right?
そう、メラ組は...
Right, so to Melagumi...
から、when I told メラ組 は...
...when I told Melagumi...
あの、I go to a gym？
...like, "I go to a gym"?
そういうこと？
Is that how it works?
知らないよね？
You don't know, right?
知ってたら怖えじゃろ？
It'd be scary if you knew, right?
知ってないじゃろ？ 知ってないじゃろ？
You don't know, right? You don't, right?
Maybe you guys don't know...
what... where gym... what gym I go でしょ？
what... where gym... what gym I go to, right?
うん、知ってたら怖いのじゃ。OK？
Yeah, it'd be scary if you knew. Okay?
OK、OK、OK、OK。
Okay, okay, okay, okay.
分かってきたのじゃ。
I'm starting to get it.
よいしょ。
Alright.
ふんふんふんふん。
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
OK。
Okay.
よいしょ。
Alright.
Here we go.
よいしょ、よいしょ。OK、OK、OK。I understand。
Alright, alright. Okay, okay, okay. I understand.
ちょっと分かってきた。
I'm getting it a bit.
じゃあ...
Then...
基本 the のことが多いな。
Basically it's "the" most of the time, isn't it?
多分 Duolingo の問題だったら...
In Duolingo questions, probably...
the のこと多い？
...is "the" more common?
うーん...
Hmm...
A response to this question could be No, I lift weights at home...
...clarifying statement。
"...a clarifying statement.'"
うーん...
Hmm...
なるほど。
I see.
OK、OK、OK、OK。日常会話だと the の方が多い。
Okay, okay, okay, okay. In daily conversation, "the" is more common.
「話し相手が友達そう」で、確かに。
"Because the person you're talking to sounds like a friend"—true.
基本的に友達とか、近い人間いっぱいおるなら the が多い。
Basically, if there are lots of friends or close people around, it's mostly "the".
Duolingo メタ、確かに。
Duolingo meta, for sure.
うんうんうんうん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
OK。
Okay.
OK、OK、OK。
Okay, okay, okay.
メラがどこのジム行ってるか分かんないけど...
You might not know which gym Mela goes to, but...
配信でよく出るなら、「いつも話してくれてるやつね」って見えて the つくパターンでしょ。
...if it comes up often on stream, people see it as "the one she always talks about", so it takes "the".
確かに！
True!
わしがもしジムの話をめっちゃ配信でしてたら...
If I talked about the gym all the time on stream...
「あー、なんかいつも話してるあのジムね！」っていうので...
...everyone would be like, "Ah, that gym she always talks about!" so...
その具体的にどこの店舗かは分かんないけど...
even if they don't know specifically which branch,
メラがいつも話している共通認識の上の「あの」で the がつくのか。
based on mutual understanding, it takes "the" for "that gym".
なるほどのじゃ。OK、OK、OK、OK。分かった。うん。
I see, noja. Okay, okay, okay, okay. Got it. Yeah.
the gym のが正しい。
"The gym" is more correct.
ジムは the gym のが自然。OK、OK、OK、OK。OK。
For gym, "the gym" is more natural. Okay, okay, okay, okay. Okay.
分かった。分かった、分かった、分かった。
Got it. Got it, got it, got it.
OK。
Okay.
ノーミスでクリア！ やったのじゃー！
Cleared with zero mistakes! I did it, noja!
分かってきた。
I'm starting to get it.
a と the is 最も難しい English...
"A" and "the" is the most difficult English...
よいしょ
All right.
初心者に、とって、イングリッシュビギナーにとって、
For beginners, for English beginners...
aとかtheとかは
things like "a" and "the"...
めっちゃ難しいからね。
are super difficult, after all.
I do karate.
I do karate. 空手、
I do karate. Karate...
空手をします。
I do karate.
Do you do yoga?
Do you do yoga? Do you doだって。doが2個つくよ。
Do you do yoga? It says "Do you do." Two "do"s!
do2個つく、Do you do?
Two "do"s. "Do you do?"
ダンスロボットダンスや。
That's like "Dance Robot Dance"!
Do you do yoga? あなたはヨガをしますか？
"Do you do yoga?" Do you do yoga?
ヨガを...しますか。
Yoga... shimasu ka.
町にひとつしかないような建物ならthe？
If it's a building that's the only one in town, is it "the"?
役所的な？役所とか。
Like a city hall? A government office or something.
セブンイレブンはtheで、いつものセブンイレブンは...
7-Eleven is "the", and the usual 7-Eleven is...
あ、いつものセブンイレブンがtheなんじゃない？
Ah, wouldn't the usual 7-Eleven be "the"?
だいたい、で、広くとるセブンイレブンがaなんじゃない？
And broadly speaking, a 7-Eleven would be "a", right?
文脈によるな。
Depends on the context.
文脈によらない、それも？
Doesn't that depend on context too?
なんかさ、例えばコンビニの中でセブンイレブンを指定するならtheだけど、
Like, if you specify 7-Eleven among convenience stores, it's "the", but...
セブンイレブンの中で、もっと細かいものの話をするならaの時もない？
if you're talking about something more specific inside 7-Eleven, isn't it "a" sometimes?
なんか、文脈によって変わるのじゃ。
It changes depending on the context, noja.
なんか、内容？内容によって変わらない？
Like, the content? Doesn't it change depending on what you mean?
その、その時話したい内容によって変わるのじゃ。
It changes depending on what you want to talk about at the time, noja.
うわ、難しい！奥が深いのじゃ！
Whoa, that's so hard! It's so deep, noja!
いつものセブンでも聞き手が知らないなら...
"Even if it's the usual 7-Eleven, if the listener doesn't know..."
ええー！奥が深いのじゃー！
Whoa! It's so deep, noja~!
My karate class is at seven.
マイカ...空手のクラスは...空手教室7時から。
My ka... Karate class is... Karate class is at 7.
My karate class is at seven.
ふんふん。7時に空手。
Mm-mm. Karate at 7 o'clock.
ちなみにわしも空手習ってたことあるのじゃ。
By the way, I used to take karate lessons too, noja.
空手、ある、のじゃ。
I've done karate, noja.
My cats do yoga too.
のじゃ？My cats do yoga too.
Noja? My cats do yoga too.
キャットも？キャットも、キャットもヨガとかするのじゃ？
Cats too? Cats... cats do yoga too, noja?
My cats do yoga too.
のじゃー。
Noja~
帯はね、全然、帯ね、白帯のまま終わったのじゃ。
Belt-wise, not at all... I ended as a white belt, noja.
あのね、すぐ、すぐ終わったのじゃ。
You know, it ended really quickly, noja.
あのね、なんでね、why I practice karateかというとね、
You see, as for why... why I practiced karate...
あの、ストロングガールに憧れたのじゃ。
I looked up to strong girls, noja.
Strong girl is so coolでしょう？そう。
"Strong girl is so cool", right? Yeah.
Strong salamander is so coolでしょう？
"Strong salamander is so cool", right?
だから、I want to be strong! 強くなりたかったんじゃが、
So, "I want to be strong!" I wanted to get strong, but...
強くなりたかったんじゃが、空手を習ったんだけど、
I wanted to get strong, so I took karate, but...
空手って戦う空手と、あの型の空手があるのじゃん。
in karate, there's fighting karate and kata karate, right?
うん、なんか、ダンスみたいな。
Yeah, like dancing.
なんかダンスみたいな覚え系の空手があって、
There's like a dance-like, memorization-based karate,
で、わしがね習ってたのが覚え系の空手なんじゃよ。
and what I was learning was that memorization-based karate.
そう、覚え系のやつ。
Yeah, the memorization kind.
なんか、あの戦う空手が習いたかったのに、
Even though I wanted to learn fighting karate,
あの、いざ教室に入ってみたら、なんか、あのー、なんじゃっけ？
once I actually joined the dojo, it was like, um... what was it?
平安初段みたいな、そういうなんか覚え空手？
Like Heian Shodan or something, like memorization karate?
覚え空手の方に配属されて、
I was assigned to the memorization karate side,
assigned to the memorization karate side,
え、わしが思ってたのと違うと思って。そう、思ってたのと違うと思って。
and I was like, "Wait, this isn't what I thought." Yeah, not what I thought.
そう、思ってたのと違ってやめたのじゃ。
Yeah, so it was different from what I thought, and I quit, noja.
わし本当は、わし本当は、あの戦いたかった。
I actually... I actually wanted to fight.
I want to fight! ファイト、ストロング空手をしたかったんじゃが、
I want to fight! I wanted to do fighting, strong karate, noja, but...
なんか、あの型、型の方にね、配属された。
somehow I was assigned to the kata, forms side.
それですごい、あのー、悲しかった。
And so, I was really sad.
そう、I'm sad. そう、で、やめた。
Yeah, "I'm sad". Yeah, and so I quit.
そう。いや、やめたのじゃー。
Yeah. So I quit, noja~
なんか思ってたのと違ったのじゃー。Yes.
It was different from what I thought, noja~ Yes.
これじゃないって言えばよかった？
Should I have said, "This isn't what I meant"?
なんか、せっかく、え、自分がやりたいって言ってさ、習い事通わせてくれたのにさ、
Like, when they let me take lessons after I said I wanted to do it,
「いや、なんかこっちじゃなくて戦うのがやりたかったのじゃ」って言うとちょっと、
saying, "No, I didn't want this, I wanted to do fighting, noja" would be a bit...
ちょっとあの、やっぱ子供ながらに、やっぱ長生きしてるからさ、
Well, even as a kid, since I've lived a long time, after all,
あの、わしがさ、その人間低学年の頃もさ、すでにさ、もう何百歳じゃったからさ、
even when I was in the lower grades of human elementary school, I was already several hundred years old,
変にさ、大人でさ、
so I was weirdly grown-up,
変に自分は大人じゃったからさ、言いづらくて。
and because I was weirdly grown-up, it was hard to say.
せっかく習わせてくれたのに、「ちょっと言うの違うかな」と思って、
They went out of their way to let me take it, so I thought, "Maybe it's not right to say that,"
そう、言い出せなかったのじゃ。
and I just couldn't bring myself to say it, noja.
言い出せなくてやめたのじゃ。のじゃ。
I couldn't say it, so I quit, noja. Noja.
Yes. This is my karate's 思い出。
Yes. This is my karate memory.
のじゃ。Yes.
Noja. Yes.
よし。
Alright.
Where can we do yoga?
でも思うけど、子供は気なんて使わなくていいのじゃ、本当は。
Though I think kids really shouldn't have to worry about pleasing others, honestly.
本来ね。
At least ideally.
本来、子供は気を使わずにやりたいことを主張していくべきなのじゃ。
Ideally, children should assert what they want to do without catering to others.
なぜなら幼少期にやりたいことを主張できないと、大人になるともっとできなくなって、
Because if you can't assert what you want as a kid, it gets even harder as an adult,
いずれそれが自分の首を絞めることになるからなのじゃ。
and eventually, that comes back to choke you.
わかるのじゃ、わし。
I know this all too well.
わしはわかっておるのじゃ。
I understand it from experience.
じゃから、わがままになってみるのも大事なのじゃ。
That's why being a little selfish is also important.
でもわがままになれる環境となれない環境っていうのもあって、
But there are environments where you can be selfish and ones where you can't,
結構、あの、お家によってはね、
and depending on your household,
わがままに主張ができないところもあるから、それもまた難しい話じゃないかって思うのじゃ。
there are places where you can't assert yourself, so that makes it a tricky topic.
んー、のじゃ。
Yeah...
環境によるのじゃ。
It depends on the environment.
いつかわがままが言える環境にお主が出会えるといいなって思いますのじゃ。
I hope you can find an environment where you can freely express yourself someday.
Where
Where can we do yoga?
どこでヨガをやりますか？
"Where do we do yoga?"
文のパターンね。
Paying attention to sentence patterns...
えーっと、これはパターンは...
Um, this pattern is...
can
えーっと、Whereとか疑問のWが冒頭にあって、はてながあるやつ。
The kind with a question "W" like "Where" at the start and a question mark at the end.
When
can
they
join us?
のじゃ。
Alright.
When can they join us?
うん。
Yeah.
オッケー。
Okay.
Yes, you can watch.
あなたは、見れます。はい。
You can watch. Yes.
見てもいいよ。
You can watch.
見てもいいよー。
You may watch~
When can we meet?
いつわしたち会えるのじゃ？
When can we meet, メラ組？
When can we meet, Mela squad?
メラ組！
Mela squad!
メラ組、When can we meet?
Mela squad, when can we meet?
いつ会えるのじゃ？
When can we meet?
Yes, your friend can join us.
友達も一緒に参加できますー。
Your friend can join in too.
We can play from five to six.
We can play from five to six. 5時から6時の間に遊べます。
We can play from five to six. We can play between five and six.
5時から6時まで一緒に遊べる。
We can play together from five to six.
うん。
Yup.
She does karate from four to five.
ちょ、でもjust now、確かに！今会ってる、
Wait, but "just now", you're right! We're meeting right now,
just now we are meeting のじゃ。イエス、確かに。
just now we are meeting! Yes, indeed.
ストリーミングで会ってるのじゃ。イエス。
We are meeting on stream. Yes.
She does karate from four to five.
1時間、4時から5時まで空手をやってます。She does.
For one hour, she does karate from four to five. She does.
She だから does なのじゃ。
Because it's "she", it takes "does".
Yes, we are meeting now. Yes, we're online, online meeting now.
オッケー。
Okay.
When can we practice... practice
When can we practice 空手？
When can we practice karate?
Where
can
I
play
can
人間
person
動詞
verb
オッケー。
Okay.
Where can I play tennis? どこでテニス遊べますか？
Where can I play tennis? Where can I play tennis?
ふんふん。
Uh-huh.
karate classes
空手クラス。空手教室！
Karate class. Karate classes!
I
do yoga every day.
うん。
Yup.
ヨガ。
Yoga.
When can we do karate?
When can we do 空手？
From five to seven.
いつ空手やる？
"When do we do karate?"
5時、7時。
"Five to seven."
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
オッケー。
Okay.
一緒に空手ができる。
"We can do karate together."
We
can
ん？
Hmm?
We can、canの後は do、We can do karate
We can... After "can" is "do", We can do karate
do 〇〇？
do something?
together じゃない？
Isn't it "together"?
We can do karate together. canの後は does じゃない、do。
We can do karate together. After "can" isn't "does", it's "do".
do
s つかない。
No "s" attached.
どこで空手ができますか？
"Where can karate be done?"
Where
can
ん？
Hmm?
Where
can...
do
karate
のじゃ？
Huh?
あ、人間を指定しなきゃいけない！
Ah! You have to specify the person!
I have to...
人間、they、何か入れなきゃいけない。
A person, "they", I had to put something in.
Where can they do karate?
誰が空手をするか、入れなきゃいけない！
I have to specify who is doing karate!
Very close、close、確かに主語がない！
Very close, close... Indeed, there's no subject!
主語がない！
There's no subject!
確かに
Indeed.
"they"なんだね
It's "they", huh?
It was "they".
"Yes, you were missing a..."
"missing a subject." サブジェクト！
"...missing a subject." Subject!
サブジェクトがいる
It needs a subject.
"Yeah, we need a subject, okay."
で、サブジェクトが"they"
And the subject is "they".
うーん
Hmm.
"Where can they..."
誰かがいる
Someone is needed.
"who"がいる
"Who" is needed.
"do karate." オッケー、分かった
"do karate." Okay, I got it.
サブジェクトがいる
You need a subject.
サブジェクト who, what. オッケー、who, what
Subject, "who", "what". Okay, "who", "what".
ふんふんふん
Mm-hmm.
"Where can do karate is who you're talking about, they."
ふーん、"who"。なるほど
Hmm, "who". I see.
せーい。オッケー
There we go. Okay.
「私たちは9時から10時まで遊びます」
"We play from 9 to 10."
あ、"We"! サブジェクト！サブジェクト！
Ah, "We"! Subject! Subject!
You guys a subject, "We" is サブジェクト！
You guys, a subject! "We" is the subject!
"We..."
あー..."play"
Um... "play"
うーーん...
Umm...
"from..."
"We play from..."
"ten"? ん？ "nine to ten"
"ten"? Huh? "nine to ten"?
"nine to ten"
うん
Yeah.
Yup.
"It needs the subject: I, we, they, he, she..."
"It needs a subject: I, we, they, he, she..."
「メラ今日賢いぜ」
"Mela is smart today."
うーん、いっぱい主語、サブジェクトがいる。オッケー、サブジェクト
Yeah, lots of subjects... needs a subject. Okay, subject.
オッケー。「どこで空手ができますか？」 えっと...
Okay. "Where can they do karate?" Um...
"Where..."
"can..."
"they"、サブジェクト！
"they", subject!
"they"
"do..."
"karate."
"Where can they do..." サブジェクト
"Where can they do..." Subject!
オッケー！サブジェクトのじゃ、"they"が入った
Okay! Subject noja, "they" is in!
オッケー
Okay.
うん、オッケー
Yeah, okay.
やったのじゃー！
I did it-noja!
"It also a subject..."
"It's also a subject..."
ふんふんふんふん。オッケー、オッケー、オッケー、オッケー
Mm-hmm. Okay, okay, okay, okay.
分かった
I get it.
分かってきた
I'm starting to get it.
オッケー
Okay.
サブジェクト is 大切
Subject is important.
果物。"fruit."
Fruit. "fruit."
オッケー
Okay.
"I eat lots of fruit."
え、果物をたくさん食べます
Um, "I eat lots of fruit."
あー、サラマンダー is...
Ah, salamanders...
サラマンダー don't eat fruit.
Salamanders don't eat fruit.
サラマンダーは果物苦手
Salamanders don't like fruit.
"Japanese assumes you know the subject,"
"so they don't say it."
日本語確かに言わないかも
True, in Japanese we might not say it.
うん、メラ don't eat fruit, actually.
Yeah, Mela doesn't eat fruit, actually.
Yes.
Yes, 偏食！
Yes, picky eater!
I'm...ねぇ
I'm... you know,
I'm 偏食なのじゃ
I'm a picky eater noja.
No fruits.
うん、苦手
Yeah, I don't like them.
"Do you like sweets?"
スイーツは好き
I like sweets.
スイーツは好き。スナック好き
I like sweets. I like snacks.
I really like snacks,
but I don't like fruits.
うん
Yeah.
うん、fruits...
Yeah, fruits...
"Bad girl?"
Yes, I'm a bad girl.
うん、好き嫌い...
Yeah, picky eating...
"How about vegetables?"
サラマンダー don't eat vegetables!
Salamanders don't eat vegetables!
Yes.
サラマンダー don't eat vegetables and fruits. うん
Salamanders don't eat vegetables and fruits. Yeah.
No, no vegetables.
No vegetables. うん
No vegetables. Yeah.
No vegetables.
Yes.
"Too cute to be bad?" Yes!
キュートだからオッケー？
Because I'm cute it's okay?
キュートだからオッケー
Because I'm cute, it's okay.
うん。Yes, I only eat 肉！
Yeah. Yes, I only eat meat!
肉、肉
Meat, meat.
"What do you eat?"
肉！
Meat!
肉！焼肉！
Meat! Yakiniku!
Yes.
肉
Meat.
No, no salad.
Only meat, yes, only meat!
Only meat.
野菜ジュースはギリ
Vegetable juice is barely okay.
野菜ジュースは飲める
I can drink vegetable juice.
うん、野菜ジュースは飲める。でも野菜ジュースが飲めるギリギリの野菜
Yeah, I can drink vegetable juice. But that's the absolute limit of veggies.
Yes.
"Do you cook it yourself with your fire?"
No, because my fire is too hot!
My fire is, あの、so...
My fire is, um, so...
temperatureが...
the temperature is...
めっちゃ灰...
It'll just turn to ashes...
あの、燃えてなくなっちゃう、
Like, it burns away to nothing...
あの、if I cook with my fire,
like, if I cook with my fire,
わしの炎で料理したら、あの、なくなる。
if I cook with my flames, well, it's just gone.
うん。なくなっちゃう。
Yeah, it just disappears.
Very hot.
Yes blue... blue fire, yes blue flame.
It's super hot.
Yeah, super hot.
What about donuts, like きょうこ？
"What about donuts, like Kyoko?"
Yes! I love donuts!
I love donuts. うん。
I love donuts. Yep.
そう、become charcoal.
Right, become charcoal.
Yes, charcoal.
そう、炭になっちゃう。
Right, it turns into charcoal.
Tomato? No tomato!
Tomatoes? No tomatoes!
Yes ketchup.
I can eat ketchup, but I can't eat tomato.
I can eat ketchup, but I can't eat tomatoes.
うん。
Yeah.
So carb?
So carbs?
So carb and meat only? Yes!
So carbs and meat only? Yes!
I... I like rice.
ライス好き。
I like rice.
But...
No tomato! No tomato!
No tomatoes! No tomatoes!
No vegetables!
うん、yes ketchup.
Yeah, yes ketchup.
うん、ケチャップはOK。
Yeah, ketchup is okay.
Yes.
うん。
Yeah.
あーっと、Melachi, do you like fish dishes?
Let's see... "Melachi, do you like fish dishes?"
うーんと、little.
Hmm, a little.
I like salmon!
サーモン好きのじゃ。
I like salmon.
うん。サーモンは好き。
Yeah. I do like salmon.
Ketchup or tomato in pasta?
Ketchup!
ケチャップ、I like ketchup.
Ketchup, I like ketchup.
うん。
Yeah.
サーモン可愛いけど、サーモン好き。
Salmon are cute, but I like eating salmon.
江戸で何食べてたか？
"What did you eat during the Edo period?"
魚！
Fish!
Fish and rice!
魚食べてたのじゃ。
I used to eat fish.
のじゃ。
Indeed.
ピザ？
Pizza?
ピザ好き。
I like pizza.
Melachi like pizza, yes! I... I like pepperoni!
Pepperoni pizza!
うん、ピザ好き。
Yeah, I like pizza.
ピザ好きー。
I love pizza.
Yes.
うん。
Yeah.
トースト好き。トースト好き。
I like toast. I like toast.
うん、ペパロニピザ好き。
Yeah, I like pepperoni pizza.
Because... why...
Okay, I, I talk about why I like pepperoni pizza.
Okay, I'll explain why I like pepperoni pizza.
Because ペパロニピザは野菜入ってない。
Because pepperoni pizza doesn't have vegetables!
そう、pepperoni pizza is...
Right, pepperoni pizza is...
大体、no vegetables じゃない？
usually no vegetables, right?
あの、マルゲリータとかは、野菜あるじゃん？
Like, margherita pizza has vegetables, right?
Tomato とかあるじゃん？
It has tomatoes and stuff, right?
But pepperoni pizza is...
あの、no vegetables, no veggies, yes!
um, no vegetables, no veggies, yes!
そう、から、I can eat.
Right, so I can eat it.
No onion! No onion.
No onions! No onions.
そう、ペパロニピザはないから食べれる。そう。
Right, pepperoni pizza doesn't have any, so I can eat it. Right.
Oh yes, yes, yes, yes.
マルゲリータたまにトマト入ってるのじゃ。
Margherita sometimes has tomatoes on it.
そう。
Yeah.
玉ねぎ、ペパロニピザ入ってなくない？
Pepperoni pizza doesn't have onions, right?
ペパロニピザ、ペパロニピザのトマトはケチャップなのじゃ。
Pepperoni pizza... The tomato on pepperoni pizza is ketchup.
うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah.
パイナップルは...
Pineapple is...
あの、フルーツだからいけない。
well, it's fruit, so it's a no-go.
あの、ピザにパイナップルとかそういうのじゃなくて、そもそも...
It's not about pineapple on pizza or anything, but first of all...
I can't eat pineapple because pineapple is a fruit.
I can't eat fruit. うん。
I can't eat fruit. Yeah.
うん。
Yeah.
Yes.
I can't eat vegetable のじゃ。
I can't eat vegetables.
Yes.
フルーツ、no fruit のじゃ。
Fruit, no fruit for me.
Okay.
No fruit.
Can't or don't like? Don't like. I don't like fruits and vegetables.
イチゴもあんま好きじゃないけど...
I don't really like strawberries either, but...
ケーキに乗ってるイチゴはギリ食べれるのじゃ。
I can just barely eat strawberries on a cake.
うん。
Yeah.
確かにフルーツ食べれないとアレルギーっぽい... アレルギーはないのじゃ。
"True, not being able to eat fruit sounds like an allergy..." I don't have allergies.
多分ないと思うのじゃ。
I don't think I have any.
うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah.
Yes. ガキメラ？
Yes. "Bratty Mela"?
えー？まあ、サラマンダーは偏食なのじゃ。イチゴ大福食べれないのじゃ。
What? Well, salamanders are picky eaters. I can't eat strawberry daifuku.
I can't eat いちご。I don't like いちご大福。
I can't eat strawberries. I don't like strawberry daifuku.
うん。
Yeah.
よし、英語やるのじゃ！
Alright, time to study English!
ちょ...
Wait...
食べ物の話しちゃった。
I ended up talking about food.
たくさんの、a lot of?
"A lot of", "a lot of"?
a lot of.
Can I drink this water?
この水を...
This water...
飲んでも...
...drink...
いいですか？
...is it okay to?
ガキ、のじゃ？
"Brat, noja"?
Mela、食べれないもの、好き嫌いが多すぎるから...
Because Mela has too many foods she dislikes...
OK, and can I eat bread?
食っちゃ寝サラマンダー？偏食？
"Eat-and-sleep salamander"? Picky eater?
事実ですのじゃ、yes。
That's a fact, noja. Yes.
OK, and can I eat bread?
パン食べてもいいのじゃ？イエス。
Is it okay to eat bread, noja? Yes.
When can you start the class?
When can you start the class? いつ授業を...
When can you start the class? When [can you]...
始められますか？
...start the class?
食生活ヤバそう。
"Your diet seems terrible."
結構食べてるけどな...
I eat quite a lot, though...
結構食べてるけど...
I eat quite a bit, but...
How can...
How can I feel better?
どうしたら気分がよくなりますか？
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy.
のじゃ？！
Noja?!
そうなの？！
Really?!
パンケーキヘルシーじゃないって？！
Pancakes aren't healthy?!
マックス、パンケーキは健康的じゃない。
Max, pancakes are not healthy.
Really?!
I... I thought pancake...
...is healthy!
Why?!
のじゃあ...
Nojaa...
あれ？違う。
Wait, it's wrong.
あ、「いいえ」が入るのか。No、「いいえ」入れてないのか。
Ah, "No" was needed. I didn't include "No"?
Sorry, 'No' 忘れてた。「いいえ」。
Sorry, I forgot "No". "Iie".
I forgot 'No', 「いいえ」。
I forgot "No", "iie".
「No」忘れてた。
I forgot "No".
のじゃ... I really like pancakes!
Noja... I really like pancakes!
I really like pancakes and I eat... ate... yesterday!
うん、昨日食べた。
Yeah, I ate them yesterday.
そう。
Yeah.
My mam が作ったパンケーキ食べたのじゃ。
I ate pancakes that my mom made, noja.
Mela, but what about tangerines?
みかんは食べれる。
I can eat tangerines.
みかん好き。
I like tangerines.
Sugar, I like sugar! I really like sugar!
Yes, Mela like sweet stuff. Yes, I really like sweet stuff!
Yes, Mela likes sweet stuff. Yes, I really like sweet stuff!
好きなのじゃ。
I like it, noja.
いや、お母さんと一緒に住んでないのじゃ、Mela！
No, Mela doesn't live with her mom, noja!
あ、I'm 一人暮らしじゃけど、My mam が、あの...
Ah, I live alone, but my mom, um...
あの、My house に来て、
...um, comes to my house,
クッキングしてくれる。作って、
and cooks for me. She makes it,
あの、なんじゃ？
and um, what is it?
冷凍してくれる。
Freezes it for me.
冷凍してくれるご飯をね、作ってね、
She makes meals to freeze,
置いてってくれるのじゃ。
and leaves them for me, noja.
そう。
Yeah.
そう、お掃除とかもしてくれる。
Yeah, she even cleans for me and stuff.
そう。
Yeah.
優しいのじゃ。
She's so kind, noja.
Yes, really kind mam.
Yes, really kind mom.
That's... yes.
お世話されてるのじゃ。
I'm being pampered, noja.
うん。Yes.
Yeah. Yes.
クッキー作ってくれた。この前 My mam が、
She made cookies for me. The other day, my mom...
ディアマンクッキー作ってくれたのじゃ。
...made diamant cookies for me, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
My mam ね、ケーキとかもね、作ってくれる。
My mom bakes cakes and stuff for me, too.
優しいのじゃ。
She's so kind, noja.
Yes.
Yeah, really kind!
kind mam のじゃ。
She's a kind mom, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
優しい。
So kind.
あ、and also, my mam... my mother...
Ah, and also, my mom... my mother...
is doing Duolingo.
My mother really like Duolingo. 毎日してる。
My mother really likes Duolingo. She does it every day.
そう、わしのね、ま、あの、母？My mother、
Yeah, my, well, um, mother? My mother...
マムがね、Duolingo をね、しててね、毎日しててね、
Mom has been doing Duolingo, doing it every day,
全部クリアしちゃったらしい！My mam!
and apparently cleared everything! My mom!
My mam ね、clear Duolingo, every... every lesson!
My mom, cleared Duolingo, every... every lesson!
全部のレッスンやっちゃったっぽくてね、
She seems to have finished every single lesson...
そう。
Yeah.
Mela's mother はね、あの、
Mela's mother, you see...
全部、全クリしてね、Duolingo 全クリしたっぽくてね、
...cleared everything, finished all of Duolingo,
で、今ね、あの、日本語？
and right now, um, Japanese?
Duolingo っていろんな言語を学べるんじゃが、あの、日本語？
You can learn all sorts of languages on Duolingo, but um, Japanese?
ん？なんじゃ？
Hm? What was it?
わし今 English 学んでるじゃろ？
I'm learning English right now, right?
I'm learning English right now, but my mother...
learning English with Duolingo complete...
コンプリートしたから、
completed it, so...
あの、My mother は今、
...um, my mother is now...
日本語を英語で学んでるのじゃ。
learning Japanese through English, noja.
My mother is learning Japanese with...
...English.
イングリッシュ？
English?
そう、もう...そう。
Yeah, she already... yeah.
全部やっちゃったから、なんか...
Since she finished all of it, like...
に...そう、英語の...
Ja-... Yeah, the English...
英語で、日本語を学んでて。
She's learning Japanese through English.
で、なんかDuolingoって、なんかいろんな正解があるじゃろう？
And with Duolingo, there are various accepted answers, right?
なんか「こういう言い方もできるよね」みたいな正解があるっぽくて、それをなんか申告してるらしい。
Apparently there are answers like "you could say it this way too," and she reports them.
Duolingoに「こういうのもあります」みたいなのを申告して、
She reports to Duolingo like, "This way is also an option,"
申告してそれが通ると、なんかメールで「あなたの申告が通りました」みたいなのが来るっぽくて。
and when it gets accepted, apparently she gets an email saying "Your suggestion was accepted."
そう。それをやってるっぽい。そう。
Yeah. Seems like she's doing that. Yeah.
そう、言語を英語に設定して日本語コースをね、学んでるっぽいのじゃ。
Yeah, she set the language to English and is learning the Japanese course, noja.
そう。そう。
Yeah. Yeah.
っていうのを、My Momがやってるっていうのを、この前教えてくれた。
She told me recently that that's what My Mom is doing.
わしが「Duolingo始めた」っつったら、「やってるよ」っつって。
When I said, "I started Duolingo," she told me, "I'm doing that too."
あの実家に帰ると、母がね、たまにね、Duolingoやってるのじゃ。
When I go home, my mom is sometimes doing Duolingo, noja.
うん、My Mom、Duolingoやってる。うん。
Yeah, My Mom is doing Duolingo. Yeah.
そう。母に英語習った方がいい、確かに。
Yeah. "Better to learn English from your mom" - true!
My motherはね、わしより英語できる。
My mother is better at English than me.
うん。
Yeah.
わしより英語できるし、
She's better at English than me,
My mother...MomもMy dadも、英語ペラペラ...ペラペラ？
and My mother... Mom and My dad are both fluent in English... Fluent?
ペラペラ...My dadは英語喋れる。
Fluent... My dad can speak English.
My dad can speak English.
My Momも maybe can speak English.
My Mom maybe can speak English, too.
I am ちょっと。I'm little. I'm little.
I am a little. I'm little. I'm little.
のじゃ。そう。
Noja. Yeah.
わしよりできる。父と母はわしよりできる。
Better than me. My dad and mom are better than me.
Eat healthy meals.
健康的な食事をとりなさい。
Yes! のじゃ。
Yes! Noja.
そう。
Yeah.
食事、meal、meal...
Meal, meal, meal...
健康的な食事をたべ...え、わしに言ってるの？
"Eat healthy me-..." Wait, is it talking to me?
I can't!
Because I like sugar.
I like sugar. I like snacks. I like sweets, のじゃ〜
I like sugar. I like snacks. I like sweets, noja~
Don't eat lots of sugar.
Duolingo...
えっ？！Don't eat lots of... 盗聴されてる！盗聴されてる！
What?! "Don't eat lots of..." I'm being bugged! I'm being bugged!
今、今わしの...わしの頭の中が盗聴されてるのじゃ！
Right now, my... my mind is being bugged, noja!
配信聞かれてるのじゃ！「Don't eat lots of sugar」って言われてる！
It's listening to my stream, noja! It's telling me, "Don't eat lots of sugar"!
Why?! ダメ？
Why?! Not allowed?
Sugarダメ？I really like sugar! ダメ？
Sugar isn't allowed? I really like sugar! Not allowed?
ダメのじゃ？
Not allowed, noja?
Don't eat lots of sugar.
自分で言わされてるのじゃ...のじゃ〜
I'm being forced to say it myself, noja... Noja~
盗聴されてる...のじゃ！
I'm being bugged... noja!
Yes!
えっ、の、の、のじゃ〜〜〜！
Eh? No-no-noja~~~!
vegetables
Yes, vegetables are very healthy for you.
I know! 知ってるー！知ってるけど！
I know! I know! I know that, but...!
Yes! 知ってるけど！
Yes! I know that, but...!
A big meal.
あ... A big meal.
Ah... A big meal.
A big meal. Meal.
知ってるけど〜！
I know that, but~!
Can you eat that big meal?
Yes, I can!
はい。「渡る」cross、「道」road、
Yes. "Cross," cross. "Road," road.
「橋」bridge、「たくさんの」lots of、「招待する」invite。
"Bridge," bridge. "Lots of," lots of. "Invite," invite.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Lots of food. Lots of food.
Lots of food! たくさんの食べ物〜
Lots of food! Lots of food~
I often... cook my meals at home.
自炊もします、のじゃ。
I cook for myself too, noja.
Yes!
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃ〜〜〜！のじゃ〜〜〜！
Noja~~~! Noja~~~!
Pancake is healthy!
パンケーキは健康的じゃ...のじゃ〜〜〜！
Pancakes are not health-... Noja~~~!
のじゃ〜！唐揚げ何にもかけないのじゃ！
Noja~! I don't put anything on fried chicken, noja!
Pancakes are healthy!
ヘルシーのじゃ〜〜〜！
They're healthy, noja~~~!
あ、マックス！
Ah, Max!
いや、マックス、パン...
No, Max, pan-...
パンケーキは
Pancakes are...
健康的じゃない
not healthy.
What?!
Pancake is healthy!
Pancakes are healthy!
のじゃ〜
Nojaaa~
これは、あ！レッスン6分の6だから、
This is... Ah, it's lesson six out of six, so...
今日はこのレッスンで終わりにしよう？
shall we finish today after this lesson?
今日はこれで終わり。
That'll be all for today.
これをやっておしまい。「このレベルを一気に振り返ってみよう！」
Let's do this and finish! "Let's review this level all in one go!"
They are yummy, but not healthy sadly
sadly? sadly?
初めて聞いた、sadly。
That's the first time I've heard "sadly".
のじゃ〜
Noja~
ヘルシーじゃない？
Not healthy?
Pancake is so yummy!
Pancakes are so yummy!
No, Max, pancakes are not healthy!
のじゃ！また言われた！
Noja! I got told that again!
また... sadly? 「さっぐりー」か？
Again... sadly? Is it "sadly"?
Sadly?
sadlyか。
Sadly, huh?
悲しいことに。
"Unfortunately."
あ、よきよき、sadly。オッケーオッケー。
Ah, nice, nice, sadly. Okay, okay.
我、我、我...
Wait, wait, wait...
ねえ、What? 何？
Hey, what?! What?
Duolingo, 何のじゃ？
Duolingo, what gives, noja?
Pancake is healthy!
Pancakes are healthy!
Pancakes are not that unhealthy by themselves...
It's usually the sugar syrup or jam you have on top that carry that idea.
確かに！
True!
はい！
Yeah!
チョコレートシロップをね、パンケーキにね、掛ける。
Pouring chocolate syrup over pancakes...
Really yummyのじゃ！
is really yummy, noja!
オーケー。
Okay.
いや、マックス、パンケーキは健康的じゃない。
"No, Max, pancakes are not healthy."
のじゃーーーー！
Nojaaaa!
メープルシロップ。
Maple syrup.
まあ、食べる、食べるが...
Well, I do eat it, but...
I like chocolate syrupのほうが好き。
I like chocolate syrup more.
More than chocolate... ん？ Better than?
More than chocolate... Hmm? "Better than"?
のじゃ？
Noja?
チョコレートシロップのほうがもっと好き。
I like chocolate syrup better.
もっと好きのじゃ。
I like it better, noja.
ホイップクリームは好き、I like whipped cream.
I like whipped cream, I like whipped cream.
Do you put whipped cream on that?
えっと...
Um...
When I eat pancake in my house...
When I eat pancakes in my house...
家で食べる時は乗せない。Only chocolate syrup.
When I eat at home, I don't put it on. Only chocolate syrup.
Better than!
More than is correct, but lots of people say better than.
I like chocolate syrup better than maple syrup.
Yes, you like chocolate more than maple syrup. Yes! Yes, yes, yes!
うん。
Yeah.
よりね。
Comparison, right?
「どこで空手ができますか？」
"Where can they do karate?"
Where...
they...
they... they... えっと、subjectみたいなやつ。Subject.
they... they... um, the subject thing. Subject.
Where they can do karate.
イエス？
Right?
うい？
Huh?
違う！違う！
Wrong! It's wrong!
Where they can...
疑問形だから？
Because it's an interrogative?
Because it's... 質問？Question?
Because it's... a question? Question?
Questionじゃから can they?
Since it's a question, it's "can they"?
あ〜！
Aah!
疑問... 確かに！canが先だ！
A question... Indeed! "Can" comes first!
Questionだから。
Because it's a question.
さっき行けてたのに！
Even though I got it right earlier!
さっき行けてた問題が行けなくなる理由、教えてあげようか？
Shall I tell you why I get questions wrong that I just got right?
あの、勘でやってるから。
Well, because I'm just guessing.
なんか、学習というか、多分ノリでやってるから、because...
Rather than actual studying, I'm probably just winging it by feel, so...
さっき合ってたのが行けなくなる。
what I got right before suddenly goes wrong.
オーケー、クエスチョン。
Okay, question.
Wow, you read fast!
「わあ、あなたは読むのが速い」
"Wow, you read fast."
うん。
Yeah.
Ben can't hike very far.
ベンはハイキングで遠くまで行けない。
うん、うん、うん。
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
I eat lots of fruit.
I eat lots of fruits.
「たくさんの果物を食べます」
"I eat lots of fruit."
No! No!
I don't eat lots of fruits.
No
I can't surf very well.
上手にサーフィンができないのじゃ
I can't surf very well, noja.
Here is the towel, catch!
タオルだよ、タオルだよ
"Here is the towel, here is the towel,"
キャッチして
"catch!"
Yes, your friend can join us.
Yes, your friend...
...can join us.
あんたの友達も来ていいよ
Your friend can come along too.
That player always catches the ball.
あのプレイヤーはいつもキャッチします
That player always catches it.
When can we play the next game?
When can we play...
...the next game? Next game.
When can we play the next game?
いつになったら次の試合を遊べますか？のじゃ
When can we play the next match, noja?
オッケー
Okay.
Can Lisa surf well?
上手にできますか？オッケー
Can she do it well? Okay.
The dog never catches the ball.
それはそうなのじゃ
Well, of course, noja.
犬はできない Dog can't, but サラマンダー can!
Dogs can't do it. Dogs can't, but salamanders can!
よし
Alright.
どこで空手ができますか？
"Where can they do karate?"
Where... 疑問、はてな、question, can
Where... question, question mark, can...
Where can they...
...do karate. Yes.
Where, question "can", and...
...subject, "they do karate".
オッケー
Okay.
のじゃー！
Nojaaa!
できたのじゃー！
I did it, nojaaa!
クリアーのじゃー！
Cleared, nojaaa!
オッケー
Okay.
Today's Duolingo コンプリートのじゃー
Today's Duolingo is complete, nojaaa!
お部屋に戻るのじゃ！よいしょー！
Back to the room, noja! Heave-ho!
のじゃEnglish コンプリートのじゃ
Noja English is complete, noja!
Today's のじゃEnglish！
Today's Noja English!
Yes!
Good! Great!
Did you have fun? Yes, really fun!
Except for the... あと「野菜食べろ」
Except for the... also "eat your veggies"...
Vegetable... "Eat vegetables", "eat healthy food" は not fun, but...
Vegetable... "Eat vegetables", "eat healthy food" wasn't fun, but...
あの、それ以外はね、うん
um, other than that, yeah.
Fun, yes!
Great work のじゃー！
Great work, nojaaa!
Yes!
Mm, not eat veggies.
Mmm, not eat veggies.
No, no, no, no! I... I don't like...
I don't like... I like pancakes! I don't like veggies.
No veggies, mm.
No fruits, no veggies.
Only meat, mm.
"Give all sugary snacks to Mela." Yes, please!
Please sugary... fruits please!
Yes.
Veggies on pancake? No! No, no, no, no, no!
Veggies on pancakes? No! No, no, no, no, no!
パンケーキはパンケーキ。クレープ好きのじゃ
Pancakes are pancakes. I like crepes, noja.
クレープ好きのじゃ
I like crepes, noja.
Yes, I like crepes.
のじゃ。あ！ねえ、前回「言う」って言って言ってなかったから言ってあげよう
Noja. Ah! Hey, I said I'd tell you last time but didn't, so I'll tell you now.
Where I learn, learn English...
Where I learned, learned English...
どこでわし英語学んだと思う？
Where do you think I learned English?
You guys...
どこでわしは英語を学んだと思いますかのじゃ？
Where do you think I learned English, noja?
うん、なんか、あの、次、次教えてあげるっつって…山？
Yeah, like, I said I'd tell you next time... The mountains?
山、mountain? Mountain?
The mountains? Mountain?
ママとパパ？Mom and dad?
Mama and papa? Mom and dad?
留学してた？留学してない。留学？
"Did you study abroad?" I didn't study abroad. Study abroad?
洋画？
Western movies?
今日子はね、あの、映画で学んだっつってたよね
Kyoko was saying that she learned from movies, right?
School?
掲示板？掲示板？！
Message boards? Message boards?!
Redditとか見てた？
"Were you browsing Reddit?"
YouTube?
英会話教室？
An English conversation school?
海外行ったことある？
"Have you ever been overseas?"
海外の山？いや、Japanese山。
A mountain overseas? No, a Japanese mountain.
Japanese mountain.
A Japanese mountain.
Yes.
Internet?
The internet?
サラマンダーに友達がいた？サラマンダー、1人のサラマンダー。
Did the salamander have friends? Salamander... just one salamander.
うん。
Yeah.
のじゃ、のじゃ、のじゃ。
Noja, noja, noja.
ENの先輩？
EN senpais?
留学してる感じない？
"Doesn't feel like you studied abroad"?
日本の英語教育？
"Japanese English education"?
アニメ？
Anime?
ボーカロイド？
Vocaloid?
帰国子女？山？
A returnee? A mountain?
アニメ？
Anime?
英語教室？
English conversation school?
じゃあ、答え！
Well then, the answer!
答えは！
The answer is...!
えっと、わしは...
Um, when I was...
ちっちゃい...ちっちゃい？
little... little?
人間低学年の頃、
Back in the lower human grades,
えっとね...
um, you see...
えっとね、海外に住んでたのじゃ！
um, I lived overseas, noja!
Yes! そう！
Yes! That's right!
帰国子女 is correct!
"Returnee" is correct!
うん。
Yep.
人間低学年の頃のわしは、
Back when I was in the lower human grades,
山から下りて、
I came down from the mountain,
父と母に拾われて、
got taken in by my father and mother,
そう、ちょっとしたときに、
and yeah, shortly after that,
あの...
um...
海外に住んでた。
I lived overseas.
うん。
Mm-hmm.
から発音だけが良い。
So that's why only my pronunciation is good.
発音だけが良いけど、
Only my pronunciation is good, but...
あの...なんじゃ？
um... what was it?
その、文法とかは分からない、のじゃ。
I don't really get grammar and stuff, noja.
うん。
Yeah.
1年しかいなかったけど。
Even though I was only there for one year.
Yes, only 1 year.
Yes, only one year.
そう、1 year 住んでて、
Yeah, I lived there for one year,
そこで英語覚えた。
and learned English there.
うん。
Mm-hmm.
Yes, Mela grew up overseas?
いや、not grew up だけど、
No, not "grew up", but...
あの、1 year にいた。
um, I was there for one year.
うん、のじゃ。
Yeah, noja.
1年で英検2級？
"Eiken Grade 2 in one year?"
現地校に行ってたから、
Because I went to a local school,
そう、1年で発音上手くなった。
yeah, my pronunciation got good in one year.
Yes, I lived overseas for 1 year.
Yes, I lived overseas for one year.
Yes.
Mm, so I remember the pronunciation,
but not the grammar.
Yes.
うん。
Mm.
そう、のじゃ。
That's right, noja.
Yes.
Study stay? Not study stay.
Um... ファミリーで、
Um... with my family,
そう、my family で、
yeah, with my family,
そう、行ったのじゃ。
yeah, I went, noja.
And I... uh... went to...
現地、現地校って何じゃ？ちょっと調べちゃおう。
Local... What's "local school" in English? Let me look it up.
えっと...
Um...
うーん...と...
Hmm...
今翻訳アプリ見とるのじゃ。
I'm looking at a translation app right now, noja.
えっと、I actually lived in ほにゃらら for year
Um, "I actually lived in [blank] for a year...
and went to は local school.
...and went to a local school."
Local school there.
Yes.
そう、local school. 最初ね、
Yeah, a local school. At first, you know,
日本人学校行ってたんじゃけど、
I went to a Japanese school, but...
何かあんま気に入らなくて、
I didn't really like it that much,
うん、気に入らなくて、
yeah, I didn't like it,
現地校に引っ越した、転校した。
so I moved—transferred to a local school.
Did you make friends? Yes! フレンズできたのじゃ！
"Did you make friends?" Yes! I made friends, noja!
フレンズできた。
I made friends.
何か、あの...
Like, um...
フレンズがね、あの、日本語で手紙とか書いてくれたよ。
My friends, you know, wrote me letters in Japanese.
Japanese letter くれた。
They gave me Japanese letters.
Kind friends いっぱいたのじゃ。
There were lots of kind friends, noja.
Yes.
Hola, can you Spanish? あ、何か...
"Hola, can you speak Spanish?" Ah, like...
あの...
um...
Spanish ね、
Spanish, you see,
何か、local school 行ってたときにね、スペイン語の授業あったのじゃ。
when I went to the local school, there was a Spanish class, noja.
Yes! Hola!
から、あの、Hola だけ分かる。
So, um, I only know "Hola".
Yes.
I, I know only Hola. うん。
I... I only know "Hola". Yeah.
Little. Yes.
A little. Yes.
Were there Japanese teachers? No! Japanese teacher も、
"Were there Japanese teachers?" No! Japanese teachers,
Japanese... uh... student もいなかったの。
and Japanese... uh... students, there were none either.
誰も。Only me.
Nobody. Only me.
Only me.
わしだけ。
Just me.
わしだけ Japanese.
Just me as Japanese.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Yes. うん。
Yes. Yeah.
Yes.
それほぼ、ほにゃららに住んでたって言ってるようなもんだわ。
That's basically like saying I lived in [censored] though.
あんま隠してないのじゃ。
I'm not really hiding it, noja.
あんま隠してないけれど、
I'm not really hiding it, but...
あの、明言はしていないのじゃ。
...I haven't explicitly stated it, noja.
Yes.
Yesなのじゃ。
Yes, noja.
サラマンダーわししかいなかったのじゃ。
I was the only salamander there, noja.
Yes. うん。
Yes. Yeah.
のじゃ。
Noja.
Yes.
So, I can speak...
...uh, English, little bit.
...uh, English, a little bit.
うん。
Yeah.
そういうことだったのじゃ。
So that's how it was, noja.
種明かし。
The secret is out.
種明かしのじゃー！
The mystery is revealed, noja-!
Yes.
うん。
Yeah.
ふん、ふん、ふん、ふん、ふん。
Mm-hmm, mm-hmm.
ふん、ふん、ふん。
Mm-hmm.
Yes.
で、あのー、日本に帰った後とかもー、
And so, even after returning to Japan and all,
その勉強？あの、Englishの授業とかはあった、
studying... um, there were English classes,
Englishクラスみたいなのはあって、
there were English classes and such,
あの、勉強はしたんじゃが、
and I did study, but...
テストとかも感覚でやってしまって、
...I ended up doing tests and things just by feel,
そう、感覚でやってしまって、気づいたら分からなくなっていた、みたいな。
Yeah, doing it by feel, and before I knew it, I didn't understand it anymore.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなっていた。
Before I knew it, it had become super difficult.
気づいたらめっちゃ難しくなってて、
Before I knew it, it got super hard,
あの、つまずいて、
and I stumbled,
あの、ボロボロになっちゃった。
and it totally fell apart.
うん、多分帰国子女あるあるだと思うんじゃが、
Yeah, I think it's a typical returnee thing, but...
あの、そう、中学、え、高校受験までは行けたんじゃが、
um, middle school, uh, I was fine up through high school entrance exams, but...
高校入って、文法とかもボロボロで分かんなくなっちゃって、
once in high school, my grammar fell apart and I didn't understand it,
あの、気づいたらもう誰よりも英語分からへんみたいになって、
and before I knew it, it was like I knew less English than anyone else,
そう、今もう、今こんな。
Yeah, so now, I'm like this.
から、えーっと、Duolingoでね？
So, um, with Duolingo, you know?
Duolingoで、えっとー、グラマー？
With Duolingo, um... grammar?
グラマーを勉強する。
I'll study grammar.
Yes.
Study grammar,
エンド、
and...
英語をもっと上手に、なりたい。
...I want to become better at English.
Yes.
I feel like you're underrate yourself. 本当？
"I feel like you underrate yourself." Really?
I'd say your English ability is better than just I know a bit. 本当？ Really?
"I'd say your English ability is better than just 'I know a bit'." Really? Really?
やったー！Thank you, のじゃ！
Yay! Thank you, noja!
Yes, vocabulary and grammar を練習したい、
Yes, I want to practice vocabulary and grammar,
と、思っていますのじゃ。
...is what I'm thinking, noja.
本当？めっちゃ上手、英語上手、めっちゃ言われる。
Really? "You're super good," "Your English is great," so many people are saying that!
やったのじゃー！Thank you, のじゃー！
Yay, noja-! Thank you, noja-!
Yes.
うん。
Yeah.
来週も、next weekも、
Next week too, next week as well,
Wednesday, Wednesday...
AM 7 Japanese Standard Time...
7 AM Japanese Standard Time...
に、イングリッシュのじゃイングリッシュをします！
I'll be doing English Noja English!
Yes, します。
Yes, I will.
うん。
Yeah.
See you next Wednesday, yes. Okay.
うん。
Yeah.
In English usually 7 AM, 7 AM.
うん。
Yeah.
Study, 塵積もなのじゃ。
Study, every little bit adds up, noja.
コツコツ勉強して、
Studying steadily,
上手になって、
getting better,
You guys と、オンリーイングリッシュストリームができるようになるまで、
until I can do English-only streams with you guys,
頑張りたいのじゃ。
I want to do my best, noja.
Yes.
Okay.
So, Tuesday evening for English speakers. Yes, yes!
そうなのじゃ。
That's right, noja.
がんばるのじゃー！
I'll do my best, noja-!
With Kyoko sometime? Yes!
やりたい！今日子とイングリッシュストリームいずれやりたいのじゃ！
I want to! I want to do an English stream with Kyoko sometime, noja!
Yes.
野菜は、no vegetables, no vegetables.
As for vegetables... no vegetables, no vegetables.
No vegetables.
Yes!
Okay, then. See you next Wednesday のじゃ。
Okay then, see you next Wednesday, noja.
最後の挨拶は、「さらばじゃ」が挨拶なので、
Our closing greeting is "sarabaja",
「さらばじゃ」でおしまいにしますのじゃ！
so we'll finish with "sarabaja", noja!
それじゃあ、everyone, see you next Wednesday のじゃ！
Well then, everyone, see you next Wednesday, noja!
さらばじゃーー！
Farewell, noja--!
ご視聴感謝なのじゃ！
[Thanks for watching, noja!]
Thank you for watching!